<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.34.0-wmf.1</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>AccessibleComputing</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>10</id>
    <redirect title="Computer accessibility" />
    <revision>
      <id>854851586</id>
      <parentid>834079434</parentid>
      <timestamp>2018-08-14T06:47:24Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Godsy</username>
        <id>23257138</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>remove from category for seeking instructions on rcats</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">#REDIRECT [[Computer accessibility]]

{{R from move}}
{{R from CamelCase}}
{{R unprintworthy}}</text>
      <sha1>42l0cvblwtb4nnupxm6wo000d27t6kf</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Anarchism</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>12</id>
    <revision>
      <id>894931025</id>
      <parentid>894931010</parentid>
      <timestamp>2019-04-30T22:23:44Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>ClueBot NG</username>
        <id>13286072</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>Reverting possible vandalism by [[Special:Contribs/Killmeplz666|Killmeplz666]] to version by Bear-rings. [[WP:CBFP|Report False Positive?]] Thanks, [[WP:CBNG|ClueBot NG]]. (3622125) (Bot)</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{redirect2|Anarchist|Anarchists|the fictional character|Anarchist (comics)|other uses|Anarchists (disambiguation)}}
{{pp-move-indef}}{{short description|Political philosophy that advocates self-governed societies}}
{{use dmy dates|date=July 2018}}
{{use British English|date=January 2014}}
{{anarchism sidebar}}
{{basic forms of government}}
'''Anarchism''' is an [[Anti-authoritarianism|anti-authoritarian]] [[political philosophy]]{{sfnm|1a1=McLaughlin|1y=2007|1p=59|2a1=Flint|2y=2009|2p=27}} that advocates [[Self-governance|self-governed]] societies based on voluntary, [[cooperative]] institutions and the rejection of [[Hierarchy|hierarchies]] those societies view as unjust. These institutions are often described as [[Stateless society|stateless societies]],{{sfnm|1a1=Craig|1y=2005|1p=14|2a1=Sheehan|2y=2003|2p=85}} although several authors have defined them more specifically as distinct institutions based on non-hierarchical or [[Free association (communism and anarchism)|free associations]].{{sfn|Suissa|2006|p=7}} Anarchism holds the [[Sovereign state|state]] to be undesirable, unnecessary and harmful.{{sfnm|1a1=Craig|1y=2005|1p=14|2a1=McLean|2a2=McMillan|2y=2003|2loc=Anarchism}}

Anarchism is often considered a [[Far-left politics|far-left]]   ideology{{sfnm|1a1=Brooks|1y=1994|1p=xi|2a1=Kahn|2y=2000|3a1=Moynihan|3y=2007}} and much of its [[Anarchist economics|economics]] and [[Anarchist law|legal philosophy]] reflect [[Libertarian socialism|anti-authoritarian interpretations]] of [[Anarcho-communism|communism]], [[Collectivist anarchism|collectivism]], [[Anarcho-syndicalism|syndicalism]], [[Mutualism (economic theory)|mutualism]], or [[participatory economics]].{{sfn|Guerin|1970|p=35|loc=Critique of authoritarian socialism}} As anarchism does not offer a fixed body of doctrine from a single particular worldview,{{sfn|Marshall|1993|pp=14–17}} many [[History of anarchism|anarchist types and traditions]] exist and varieties of anarchy diverge widely.{{sfn|Sylvan|2007|p=262}} [[Anarchist schools of thought]] can differ fundamentally, supporting anything from extreme [[individualism]] to complete [[collectivism]].{{sfn|McLean|McMillan|2003|loc=Anarchism}} Strains of anarchism have often been divided into the categories of [[Social anarchism|social]] and [[individualist anarchism]], or similar dual classifications.{{sfnm|1a1=Ostergaard|1y=2009|1p=14|1loc=Anarchism|2a1=Kropotkin|2y=2002|2p=5|3a1=Fowler|3y=1972}}

== Etymology, terminology and definition ==
{{see also|Anarchist terminology}}
The etymological origin of anarchism derives from ancient Greek word ''anarkhia''. ''Anarkhia'' meant &quot;without a ruler&quot; as it was composed by the prefix a  (i.e. &quot;without&quot;) and the word ''arkhos'' (i.e. leader or ruler). The suffix [[-ism]] is used to denote the ideological current that favours anarchism.{{sfnm|1a1=Bates|1y=2017|1p=128|2a1=Long|2y=2013|2p=217}} The first known use of this word was in 1642.{{sfn|Definition of Anarchism by Merriam-Webster| 2019}} Various factions within the [[French Revolution]] labelled opponents as anarchists  although few shared many views of later anarchists. There would be many revolutionaries of the early 19th century who contributed to the anarchist doctrines of the next generation, such as [[William Godwin]] and [[Wilhelm Weitling]], but they did not use the word anarchist or anarchism in describing themselves or their beliefs.{{sfn|Joll|1964|pp=27–37}}

The first political philosopher to call himself an anarchist was [[Pierre-Joseph Proudhon]], marking the formal birth of anarchism in the mid-19th century. Since the 1890s and beginning in France,{{sfn|Nettlau|1996|p=162}} the term [[libertarianism]] has often been used as a synonym for anarchism{{sfn|Guerin|1970|loc=The Basic Ideas of Anarchism}} and its use as a synonym is still common outside the United States.{{sfnm|1a1=Ward|1y=2004|1p=62|2a1=Goodway|2y=2006|2p=4|3a1=Skirda|3y=2002|3p=183|4a1=Fernández|4y=2009|4p=9}} On the other hand, some use libertarianism to refer to [[Individualist anarchism|individualistic free-market philosophy]] only, referring to [[free-market anarchism]] as libertarian anarchism.{{sfn|Morris|2002|p=61}}

While [[Anti-statism|opposition to the state]] is central, defining anarchism is not an easy task as there is a lot of talk among scholars and anarchists on the matter and various currents perceive anarchism slightly differently.{{sfn|Long|2013|p=217}} Hence, it might be true to say that anarchism is a cluster of political philosophies opposing [[authority]] and [[hierarchical organization]] (including the [[State (polity)|state]], [[Anarchism and capitalism|capitalism]], [[Anarchism and nationalism|nationalism]] and all associated [[institution]]s) in the conduct of all [[human relations]] in favour of a society based on [[voluntary association]], [[freedom]] and [[decentralisation]], but this definition has its own shortcomings as the definition based on etymology (which is simply a negation of a ruler), or based on anti-statism (anarchism is much more than that) or even the anti-authoritarian (which is an ''a posteriori'' concussion).{{sfnm|1a1=Long|1y=2013|1p=217|2a1=McLaughlin|2y=2007|2pp=25–29}} Major elements of the definition of anarchism include: a) the will for a non coercive society; b) the rejection of the state apparatus; c) belief in human nature, although it is even harder to define it than anarchism; and d) a suggestion on how to act to pursue the ideal of [[anarchy]].{{sfn|McLaughlin|2007|pp=25–26}}

== History ==
{{main|History of anarchism}}

=== Prehistoric and ancient world ===
[[File:Paolo Monti - Servizio fotografico (Napoli, 1969) - BEIC 6353768.jpg|thumb|140px|[[Zeno of Citium]] (c. 334 – c. 262 BC), whose ''[[Republic (Zeno)|Republic]]'' inspired 19th century anarchist philosopher [[Peter Kropotkin]]{{sfn|Marshall|1993|p=70}}]]
During the prehistoric era of mankind, an established authority did not exist. It was after the creation of towns and cities that hierarchy was invented and anarchistic ideas espoused as a reaction.{{sfn|Graham|2005|pp=xi–xiv}} Most notable examples of anarchism in the ancient world were in [[History of China|China]] and [[Ancient Greece|Greece]]. In China, [[philosophical anarchism]], meaning peaceful delegitimizing of the state, was delineated by [[Taoism|Taoist philosophers]] (i.e. [[Zhuang Zhou|Zhuangzi]] and [[Lao Tzu]]).{{sfnm|1a1=Coutinho|1y=2016|2a1=Marshall|2y=1993|2p=54}} Likewise in Greece, anarchist attitudes were articulated by tragedians and philosophers. [[Aeschylus]] and [[Sophocles]] used the myth of [[Antigone]] to illustrate the conflict of [[autonomy|personal autonomy]] with the state rules. Socrates questioned Athenian authorities constantly and insisted to the right of individual freedom of consciousness. [[Cynicism (philosophy)|Cynics]] dismissed human law (''Nomos'') and associated authorities while trying to live according to nature (''physis''). [[Stoics]] were supportive of a society based on unofficial and friendly relations among its citizens without the presence of a state.{{sfn|Marshall|1993|pp=4, 66–73}}

During the [[Middle Ages]], there was no anarchistic activity except some ascetic religious movements in the Islamic world or in Christian Europe. This kind of tradition later gave birth to [[religious anarchism]]. In Persia, a [[Zoroastrianism|Zoroastrian Prophet]] known as [[Mazdak]] was calling for an [[Egalitarianism|egalitarian society]] and the [[abolition of monarchy]], but he soon found himself executed by the king.{{sfn|Marshall|1993|p=86}} In [[Basra]], religious sects preached against the state. In Europe, various sects developed anti-state and libertarian tendencies. Those currents were the precursor of religious anarchism in the centuries to come. It was in the [[Renaissance]] and with the spread of [[Rationalism|reasoning]] and [[humanism]] through Europe that libertarian ideas emerged. Writers were outlining in their novels ideal societies that were based not on coercion but voluntarism. The [[Age of Enlightenment|Enlightenment]] further pushed towards anarchism with the optimism for social progress.

=== Classical anarchism ===
The turning point towards anarchism was the [[French Revolution]] in which the anti-state and federalist sentiments began to take a form, mostly by [[Enragés]] and ''[[sans-culottes]]''.{{sfn|Marshall|1993|p=4}} Some prominent figures of anarchism begun developing the first anarchist currents.{{sfn|Marshall|1993|pp=4–5}} That is the era of classical anarchism that lasted until the end of the Spanish Civil War of 1936 and was the golden age of anarchism. [[William Godwin]] espoused [[philosophical anarchism]] in England morally delegitimizing the state, [[Max Stirner]]'s thinking paved the way to individualism and [[Pierre-Joseph Proudhon]]'s theory of [[Mutualism (economic theory)|mutualism]] found fertile soil in France.{{sfn|Marshall|1993|pp=4–5}}

[[File:Bakunin.png|thumb|upright|Anarchist [[Mikhail Bakunin]] opposed the [[Marxism|Marxist]] aim of [[dictatorship of the proletariat]] in favour of universal rebellion and allied himself with the federalists in the [[International Workingmen's Association|First International]] before his expulsion by the Marxists]]
[[Michael Bakunin]] took mutualism and extended it to [[collectivist anarchism]]. Bakunin's current ([[Jura Federation]]) entered the class worker union called the [[International Workingmen's Association]] (IWA), later known as the First International, formed in 1864 to unite diverse revolutionary currents. Due to its links to active workers' movements, the International became a significant organisation. [[Karl Marx]] became a leading figure in the International and a member of its General Council. Proudhon's followers, the [[Mutualism (economic theory)|mutualists]], opposed Marx's [[state socialism]], advocating political [[abstentionism]] and small property holdings.{{sfnm|1a1=Dodson|1y=2002|1p=312|2a1=Thomas|2y=1985|2p=187|3a1=Chaliand|3a2=Blin|3y=2007|3p=116}} Bakunin's followers entered a bitter dispute with Karl Marx which ended with the split of the workers movement that officially took place in the [[Hague Congress (1872)|Fifth Congress of the IWA in the Hague, 1872]].{{sfnm|1a1=Graham|1y=2019|1pp=334–336|2a1=Marshall|2y=1993|2p=24}} The major reason lay in fundamentally different approaches on how the workers would emancipate themselves. Marx was advocating for the creation of a political party to take part in electoral struggles whereas Bakunin thought that the whole set of Marx's thinking was very authoritarian.{{sfn|Marshall|1993|pp=24–25}} Bakunin is famous for predicting that if such a party would gain power by Marxist's terms, it would end up to be the new tyrant of workers. After being expelled from the IWA, anarchists formed the [[Anarchist St. Imier International|St. Imier International]]. Under the influence of [[Peter Kropotkin]], a Russian philosopher and scientist, [[anarcho-communism]] overlapped collectivism.{{sfn|Marshall|1993|p=5}} Anarcho-communists, who drew inspiration from the 1871 [[Paris Commune]], advocated for free federation and distribution of goods according to one needs.{{sfn|Graham|2005|p=xii}} The major argument of anarcho-communism was that Bakunian perspective would lead to antagonism among collectives.

At the turning of the century, anarchism has spread all over the world.{{sfn|Moya|2015|p=327}} In China, small groups of students imported the humanistic pro-science version of anarcho-communism.{{sfn|Marshall|1993|pp=519–521}} Tokyo was a hotspot for rebellious youth from countries of the far east, pouring into Japanese capital to study.{{sfnm|1a1=Dirlik|1y=1991|1p=133|2a1=Ramnath|2y=2019|2pp=681–682}} In [[Latin America]], [[Anarchism in Argentina|São Paulo]] was a stronghold and anarchosyndicalism was the most prominent left-wing ideology.{{sfnm|1a1=Levy|1y=2011|1p=23|2a1=Laursen|2y=2019|2p=157|3a1=Marshall|3y=1993|3pp=504–508}} During that time, a minority of anarchists embarked into utilizing of violence in order to achieve their political ends. This kind of strategy is named as [[propaganda by the deed]].{{sfn|Marshall|1993|pp=633–636}} The dismemberment of the French socialist movement into many groups and the execution and exile of many [[Communards]] to penal colonies following the suppression of the Paris Commune favoured individualist political expression and acts.{{sfn|Anderson|2004}} Even though many anarchists distanced themselves to those terrorist acts, anarchists were persecuted and were given bad fame.{{sfn|Marshall|1993|pp=633–636}} [[Illegalism]], stealing the possessions of the rich because capitalists were not their rightful owners, was another strategy some anarchist adopted during the same years.{{sfn|Bantman|2019|p=374}}

[[File:Makhno group.jpg|thumb|left|[[Nestor Makhno]] with members of the anarchist [[Revolutionary Insurrectionary Army of Ukraine]]]]
Anarchists took part enthusiastically in the [[Russian Revolution]]. During the revolution, anarchists had concerns, but they opted for the revolution rather than supporting the [[White movement|Whites]]. However, they met harsh suppression after the [[Bolshevik government]] was stabilized. Anarchists in central Russia were either imprisoned, driven underground or joined the victorious [[Bolsheviks]]. Anarchists from Petrograd and Moscow instead fled to Ukraine.{{sfn|Avrich|2006|p=204}} The [[Kronstadt rebellion]] and [[Nestor Makhno]]'s struggle in the [[Free Territory]] were the most notable examples. With the anarchists being crashed in Russia, two new antithetical currents emerged, namely [[platformism]] and [[synthesis anarchism]]. Platformists sought to create a coherent group that would push for the revolution while the latter were against anything that would resemble a political party. The victory of the Bolsheviks in the [[October Revolution]] and the resulting [[Russian Civil War]] did serious damage to anarchist movements internationally. Many workers and activists saw the Bolshevik success as setting an example and [[Communist party|communist parties]] grew at the expense of anarchism and other socialist movements. In France and the United States, members of the major syndicalist movements of the [[General Confederation of Labour (France)|General Confederation of Labour]] and [[Industrial Workers of the World]] (IWW) left the organisations and joined the [[Communist International]].{{sfn|Nomad|1966|p=88}}

In the [[Spanish Civil War]], anarchists and syndicalists ([[Confederación Nacional del Trabajo|CNT]] and [[Federación Anarquista Ibérica|FAI]]) once again allied themselves with various currents of leftists. Spain had a long [[Anarchism in Spain|anarchist tradition]] and anarchists played an important role in the Civil War. In response to the army rebellion, an anarchist-inspired movement of peasants and workers, supported by armed militias, took control of [[Barcelona]] and of large areas of rural Spain where they [[Collective farming|collectivised]] the land.{{sfn|Bolloten|1984|p=1107}} The Soviet Union provided some limited assistance at the beginning of the Civil War, but as [[Joseph Stalin]] tried to seize control of the [[Republican faction (Spanish Civil War)|Republicans]] the result was a bitter fight among communists and anarchists (i.e. at a series of events named [[May Days]]).{{sfn|Marshall|1993|pp=xi &amp; 466}}

=== Post-World War II anarchism ===
[[File:Rojava Sewing Cooperative.jpg|thumb|[[Rojava]] is supporting efforts for workers to form cooperatives, such as this sewing cooperative]]
In the first years after World War II, the anarchist movement was severely damaged.{{sfn|Marshall|1993|p=xi}} However, the 1960s witnessed a revival of anarchism. The main causes of such a revival may have been the perceived failure of [[Marxism–Leninism]] and the tension build by the [[Cold War]].{{sfn|Marshall|1993|p=539}} During this era, anarchism was mostly part of other movements critical to both the state and capitalism such as the [[Anti-nuclear movement|anti-nuclear]], [[Environmental movement|environmental]] and [[Peace movement|pacifist movements]], the [[New Left]], or the [[counterculture of the 1960s]].{{sfn|Marshall|1993|pp=xi &amp; 539}} Anarchism was also associated with the [[punk rock]] movement as exemplified by bands such as [[Crass]] and the [[Sex Pistols]].{{sfn|Marshall|1993|pp=493–494}} Although [[feminist]] tendencies have always been a part of the anarchist movement in the form of [[anarcha-feminism]], they returned with vigour during the [[second wave of feminism]] in the 1960s.{{sfn|Marshall|1993|pp=556–557}}

Around the turn of the 21st century, anarchism grew in popularity and influence as part of the [[anti-war]], [[anti-capitalist]] and [[anti-globalisation movement]]s.{{sfn|Rupert|2006|p=66}} Anarchists became known for their involvement in protests against the meetings of the [[World Trade Organization]] (WTO), [[Group of Eight]] (G8) and the [[World Economic Forum]] (WEF). Some anarchist factions at these protests engaged in [[riot]]ing, [[property destruction]] and violent confrontations with the [[police]]. These actions were precipitated by ''ad hoc'', leaderless, anonymous cadres known as [[black bloc]]s—other organisational tactics pioneered in this time include [[security culture]], [[affinity group]]s and the use of decentralised technologies such as the internet. A significant event of this period was the confrontations at the [[1999 Seattle WTO protests|WTO conference in Seattle in 1999]].{{sfn|Rupert|2006|p=66}} Anarchist ideas have been influential in the development of the [[Zapatista Army of National Liberation|Zapatistas]] in Chiapas, Mexico, and the Democratic Federation of Northern Syria, more commonly known as [[Rojava]], a ''de facto'' [[Permanent autonomous zone|autonomous region]] in northern [[Syria]].{{sfn|Ramnath|2019|p=691}}

== Anarchist schools of thought ==
{{main|Anarchist schools of thought}}
[[Anarchist schools of thought]] had been generally grouped in two main historical traditions ([[individualist anarchism]] and [[social anarchism]]) which have some different origins, values and evolution.{{sfnm|1a1=McLean|1a2=McMillan|1y=2003|1loc= Anarchism|2a1=Ostergaard|2y=2003|2p=14|2loc= Anarchism}} The individualist wing of anarchism emphasises [[negative liberty]] (opposition to state or [[social control]] over the individual) while those in the social wing emphasise [[positive liberty]] to achieve one's potential and argue that humans have needs that society ought to fulfil, &quot;recognising equality of entitlement&quot;.{{sfn|Harrison|Boyd|2003|p=251}} In a chronological and theoretical sense, there are classical—those created throughout the 19th century—and post-classical anarchist schools—those created since the mid-20th century and after.

Beyond the specific factions of anarchist thought is [[philosophical anarchism]] which the theoretical stance that the state lacks moral legitimacy without accepting the imperative of revolution to eliminate it. A component especially of individualist anarchism,{{sfnm|1a1=Ostergaard|1y=2006|1p=12|2a1=Gabardi|2y=1986|2pp=300–302}} philosophical anarchism may accept the existence of a [[Minarchism|minimal state]] as unfortunate and usually temporary, necessary evil, but argue that citizens do not have a [[moral obligation]] to obey the state when its laws conflict with individual autonomy.{{sfn|Klosko|2005|p=4}} One reaction against sectarianism within the anarchist milieu was [[anarchism without adjectives]], a call for [[toleration]] first adopted by [[Fernando Tarrida del Mármol]] in 1889 in response to the bitter debates of anarchist theory at the time.{{sfn|Avrich|1996|p=6}} In abandoning the hyphenated anarchisms (i.e. collectivist-, communist-, mutualist- and individualist-anarchism), it sought to emphasise the [[anti-authoritarian]] beliefs common to all anarchist schools of thought.{{sfn|Esenwein|1989|p=135}} The various anarchist schools of thought or currents are not distinct entities, but intermingle with each other.{{sfn|Marshall|1993|pp=1–6}}

=== Classical ===
[[File:Portrait of Pierre Joseph Proudhon 1865.jpg|thumb|upright|[[Pierre-Joseph Proudhon]] was the primary proponent of [[Mutualism (economic theory)|anarcho-mutualism]] and influenced many future [[Individualist anarchism|individualist anarchist]] and [[Social anarchism|social anarchist]] thinkers]]
[[Collectivist anarchism|Collectivist]], [[Anarcho-communism|communist]] and [[anarcho-syndicalism]] are considered a form of [[social anarchism]]. [[Mutualism (economic theory)|Mutualism]] and [[Individualist anarchism|individualism]] were the other notable anarchist currents through the 19th and early 20th century. Social anarchism rejects [[Private property#Criticism|private property]], seeing it as a source of social inequality (while retaining respect for [[personal property]]) and emphasises cooperation and [[Mutual aid (organization)|mutual aid]].{{sfn|Ostergaard|1991|p=21}}

==== Mutualism ====
{{main|Mutualism (economic theory)}}
[[Mutualism (economic theory)|Mutualism]] began in 18th-century English and French labour movements before taking an anarchist form associated with [[Pierre-Joseph Proudhon]] in France and others in the United States.{{sfn|Wilburn|2019|pp=213–218}} Proudhon proposed spontaneous order, whereby organisation emerges without central authority, a &quot;positive anarchy&quot; where order arises when everybody does &quot;what he wishes and only what he wishes&quot;{{sfn|Graham|2015|loc=Chapter One: Anarchism before the International}} and where &quot;business transactions alone produce the social order&quot;.{{sfnm|1a1=Copleston|1y=2003|1p=69|2a1=Supek|2y=1975|2p=94|2ps=: The exact quote of Proudhon is the following: &quot;The notion of anarchy in politics is just as rational and positive as any other. It means that once industrial functions have taken over from political functions, then business transactions alone produce the social order&quot; (1864).}}

Proudhon distinguished between ideal political possibilities and practical governance. For this reason, much in contrast to some of his theoretical statements concerning ultimate spontaneous self-governance, Proudhon was heavily involved in French parliamentary politics and allied himself with the socialist factions of the workers movement. During his life of public service, he began advocating state-protected [[charter]]s for worker-owned [[cooperative]]s and promoting certain [[nationalisation]] schemes.{{cn|date=March 2019}}

Mutualist anarchism is concerned with [[Reciprocity (cultural anthropology)|reciprocity]], [[Free association (Marxism and anarchism)|free association]], voluntary [[contract]], [[federation]] and [[Monetary reform|credit and currency reform]]. According to the American mutualist [[William Batchelder Greene]], each worker in the mutualist system would receive &quot;just and exact pay for his work; services equivalent in cost being exchangeable for services equivalent in cost, without profit or discount&quot;.{{sfn|Greene|1875}} Mutualism has been retrospectively characterised as ideologically situated between individualist and collectivist forms of anarchism.{{sfnm|1a1=Avrich|1y=1996|1p=6|2a1=Miller|2y=1991|2p=11}} Proudhon first characterised his goal as a &quot;third form of society, the synthesis of communism and property [which] we call LIBERTY&quot;.{{sfn|Pierson|2013|p=187|ps=: The quote is from Proudhon's ''[[What is Property?]]'' (1840).}}

==== Collectivist anarchism ====
{{main|Collectivist anarchism}}
[[Collectivist anarchism]], also referred to as [[revolutionary socialism]] or a form of such,{{sfnm|1a1=Morris|1y=1993|1p=76|2a1=Rae|2y=1901|2p=261}} is a revolutionary form of anarchism, commonly associated with [[Mikhail Bakunin]] and [[Johann Most]].{{sfn|Avrich|2006|p=5}}

At the epicentre of collectivist anarchism lies the belief in the potential of humankind for goodness and solidarity which will flourish when oppressive governments are abolished.{{sfn|Heywood|2017|pp=146–147}} Collectivist anarchists oppose all private ownership of the means of production, instead advocating that ownership be collectivised. This was to be achieved through violent revolution, first starting with a small cohesive group through acts of violence, or propaganda by the deed, to inspire the workers as a whole to revolt and forcibly collectivise the means of production.{{sfn|Avrich|1996|pp=3–4}} However, collectivisation was not to be extended to the distribution of income as workers would be paid according to time worked, rather than receiving goods being distributed according to need as in anarcho-communism. This position was criticised by anarcho-communists as effectively &quot;uphold[ing] the wages system&quot;.{{sfn|Kropotkin|2007|loc=chapter 13}} Collectivist anarchism arose contemporaneously with [[Marxism]], but it opposed the Marxist [[dictatorship of the proletariat]] despite the stated Marxist goal of a collectivist [[stateless society]].{{sfnm|1a1=Heywood|1y=2017|1pp=146–147|2a1=Bakunin|2y=1990|2ps=:&quot;They [the Marxists] maintain that only a dictatorship—their dictatorship, of course—can create the will of the people, while our answer to this is: No dictatorship can have any other aim but that of self-perpetuation, and it can beget only slavery in the people tolerating it; freedom can be created only by freedom, that is, by a universal rebellion on the part of the people and free organization of the toiling masses from the bottom up&quot;.}}

Anarchist, communist and collectivist ideas are not [[mutually exclusive]]—although the collectivist anarchists advocated [[Labour voucher|compensation for labour]], some held out the possibility of a post-revolutionary transition to a communist system of distribution according to need.{{sfn|Guillaume|1972}}

==== Anarcho-communism ====
{{main|Anarcho-communism}}
{{anarcho-communism sidebar|concepts}}
[[File:Kropotkin2.jpg|thumb|left|upright|[[Peter Kropotkin]] was influential in the development of [[anarcho-communism]]]]
[[Anarcho-communism]], also known as [[anarchist-communism]], [[communist anarchism]] and [[libertarian communism]], is a theory of anarchism that advocates abolition of the [[State (polity)|state]], [[Market (economics)|markets]], [[money]], [[private property]] (while retaining respect for [[personal property]]){{sfn|Berkman|1929|ps=: Berkman explains: &quot;The revolution abolishes private ownership of the means of production and distribution, and with it goes capitalistic business. Personal possession remains only in the things you use. Thus, your watch is your own, but the watch factory belongs to the people&quot;.}} and [[capitalism]] in favour of [[common ownership]] of the [[means of production]],{{sfn|Mayne|1999|p=131}} [[direct democracy]] and a [[Horizontalidad|horizontal network]] of [[voluntary association]]s and [[workers' council]]s with production and consumption based on the guiding principle: &quot;[[From each according to his ability, to each according to his needs|From each according to his ability, to each according to his need]]&quot;.{{sfnm|1a1=Marshall|1y=1993|1p=327|2a1=Turcato|2y=2019|2pp=237–323}}

Anarcho-communism developed out of radical socialist currents after the [[French Revolution]],{{sfn|Graham|2005}} but it was first formulated as such in the Italian section of the [[First International]].{{sfn|Pernicone|2009|pp=111–113}} The theoretical work of [[Peter Kropotkin]] took importance later as it expanded and developed pro-organisationalist and insurrectionary anti-organisationalist sections.{{sfn|Pengam}}

To date, the best known examples of an anarcho-communist society (i.e. established around the ideas as they exist today and achieving worldwide attention and knowledge in the historical canon), are the anarchist territories during the [[Spanish Revolution of 1936|Spanish Revolution]]{{sfn|Bookchin|2009|loc=Chapter 1. An Overview of the Spanish Libertarian Movement}} and the [[Free Territory]] during the [[Russian Revolution]]. Through the efforts and influence of the [[Anarchism in Spain|Spanish anarchists]] during the Spanish Revolution within the [[Spanish Civil War]] starting in 1936, anarcho-communism existed in most of Aragon, parts of the Levante and Andalusia as well as in the stronghold of [[Revolutionary Catalonia|Catalonia]]. Along with the [[Republican faction (Spanish Civil War)|Republicans]], it was crushed by the combined forces of the [[Francisco Franco]]'s [[Nationalist faction (Spanish Civil War)|Nationalists]], [[Adolf Hitler]] and [[Benito Mussolini]] as well as repression by the [[Communist Party of Spain]] (backed by the [[Soviet Union]]) and economic and armaments blockades from the capitalist countries and the [[Second Spanish Republic|Spanish Republic]] itself.{{sfn|Bookchin|2009|ps=: Bookchin's quote: &quot;This process of education and class organization, more than any single factor in Spain, produced the collectives. And to the degree that the CNT-FAI (for the two organizations became fatally coupled after July 1936) exercised the major influence in an area, the collectives proved to be generally more durable, communist and resistant to Stalinist counterrevolution than other republican-held areas of Spain&quot;.}}

==== Anarcho-syndicalism ====
{{main|Anarcho-syndicalism}}
[[File:Manifestación CNT Bilbao.jpg|thumb|left|[[International Workers' Day|May Day]] 2010 demonstration of Spanish [[Anarcho-syndicalism|anarcho-syndicalist]] trade union [[Confederación Nacional del Trabajo|CNT]] in Bilbao, Basque Country]]
[[Anarcho-syndicalism]] is a branch of anarchism that focuses on the [[labour movement]].{{sfn|Isaacs|Sparks|2004|p=248}}

Anarcho-syndicalists view labour unions as a potential force for revolutionary social change, replacing capitalism and the state with a new society democratically self-managed by workers. The basic principles of anarcho-syndicalism are workers' [[solidarity]], [[direct action]] and [[workers' self-management]]. Anarcho-syndicalists believe that only direct action—that is, action concentrated on directly attaining a goal as opposed to indirect action such as electing a representative to a government position—will allow workers to liberate themselves.{{sfn|Rocker|2004|p=73}}

Moreover, anarcho-syndicalists believe that workers' organisations (the organisations that struggle against the wage system which in anarcho-syndicalist theory will eventually form the basis of a new society) should be self-managing. They should not have bosses or business agents—rather, the workers should be able to make all the decisions that affect them themselves. [[Rudolf Rocker]] was one of the most popular voices in the anarcho-syndicalist movement. He outlined a view of the origins of the movement, what it sought and why it was important to the future of labour in his 1938 pamphlet ''Anarcho-Syndicalism''. The [[International Workers Association]] is an international anarcho-syndicalist federation of various labour unions from different countries. The Spanish [[Confederación Nacional del Trabajo|CNT]] played and still plays a major role in the Spanish labour movement. It was also an important force in the Spanish Civil War.{{sfn|Heywood|2017|pp=148–149}}

==== Individualist anarchism ====
{{main|Individualist anarchism}}
[[Individualist anarchism]] refers to several traditions of thought within the anarchist movement that emphasise the [[individual]] and their [[Will (philosophy)|will]] over any kinds of external determinants such as groups, society, traditions and ideological systems.{{sfn|Ryner|2007}} Individualist anarchism is not a single philosophy, but it instead refers to a group of individualistic philosophies that sometimes are in conflict.

In 1793, [[William Godwin]], who has often been cited as the first anarchist, wrote ''[[Political Justice]]'', which some consider the first expression of anarchism.{{sfnm|1a1=Everhart|1y=1982|1p=115|2a1=Philp|2y=2006|3a1=Adams|3y=2001|3p=116}} Godwin was a philosophical anarchist and from a [[rationalist]] and [[utilitarian]] basis opposed revolutionary action and saw a [[Limited government|minimal state]] as a present &quot;necessary evil&quot; that would become increasingly irrelevant and powerless by the gradual spread of knowledge.{{sfnm|1a1=Philp|1y=2006|2a1=Godwin|2y=1798}} Godwin advocated individualism, proposing that all cooperation in labour be eliminated on the premise that this would be most conducive with the general good.{{sfn|McLaughlin|2007|p=117}}

[[File:Max stirner.jpg|thumb|left|[[Max Stirner]] (here in a sketch by [[Friedrich Engels]]) is usually considered a prominent early individualist anarchist]]
An influential form of individualist anarchism called egoism,{{sfn|Goodway|2006|p=99}} or [[egoist anarchism]], was expounded by one of the earliest and best-known proponents of individualist anarchism, the German [[Max Stirner]].{{sfn|Leopold|2006}} Stirner's ''[[The Ego and Its Own]]'', published in 1844, is a founding text of the philosophy.{{sfn|Leopold|2006}} According to Stirner, the only limitation on the rights of individuals is their power to obtain what they desire without regard for God, state, or morality.{{sfn|Miller|1991|p=11}} To Stirner, rights were &quot;[[Reification (fallacy)|spooks]]&quot; in the mind and he held that society does not exist, but &quot;the individuals are its reality&quot;.{{sfn|Ossar|1980|p=27}} Stirner advocated self-assertion and foresaw [[Union of egoists|unions of egoists]], non-systematic associations continually renewed by all parties' support through an act of will,{{sfn|Ryley|2019|p=228}} which Stirner proposed as a form of organisation in place of the state.{{sfn|Thomas|1985|p=142}} Egoist anarchists argue that egoism will foster genuine and spontaneous union between individuals.{{sfn|Carlson|1972|loc=chapter: Philosophical Egoism: German Antecedents}} &quot;Egoism&quot; has inspired many interpretations of Stirner's philosophy. It was re-discovered and promoted by German philosophical anarchist and [[homosexual]] activist [[John Henry Mackay]].

[[Josiah Warren]] was a pioneer American anarcho-individualist, who drew inspiration from Proudhon.{{sfn|Marshall|1993|pp=384–385}} [[Henry David Thoreau]] (1817–1862) was an important early influence in individualist anarchist thought in the United States and Europe. Thoreau was an American author, poet, naturalist, tax resister, [[Development criticism|development critic]], surveyor, historian, philosopher and leading [[transcendentalist]]. He is best known for his books ''[[Walden]]'', a reflection upon [[simple living]] in natural surroundings, as well as his essay, ''[[Civil Disobedience (Thoreau)|Civil Disobedience]]'', an argument for individual resistance to civil government in moral opposition to an unjust state. Benjamin Tucker later fused Stirner's egoism with the economics of Warren and Proudhon in his eclectic influential publication ''[[Liberty (1881–1908)|Liberty]]''.

From these early influences, individualist anarchism in different countries attracted a small yet diverse following of Bohemian artists and intellectuals,{{sfn|Marshall|1993|p=440}} [[free love]] and [[birth control]] advocates (see [[anarchism and issues related to love and sex]]),{{sfnm|1a1=McElroy|1y=1996|2a1=Díez|2y=2006}} individualist [[naturist]]s and [[nudist]]s (see [[anarcho-naturism]]),{{sfnm|1a1=Díez|1y=2006|2a1=Ytak|2y=2000}} [[freethought]] and [[anti-clerical]] activists{{sfnm|1a1=McElroy|1y=1981|1pp=291–304|2a1=Díez|2y=2007|2p=143}} as well as young anarchist outlaws in what became known as illegalism and [[individual reclamation]]{{sfnm|1a1=Imrie|1y=1994|2a1=Parry|2y=1987|2p=15}} (see [[European individualist anarchism]] and [[individualist anarchism in France]]). These authors and activists included [[Oscar Wilde]], [[Emile Armand]], [[Han Ryner]], [[Henri Zisly]], [[Renzo Novatore]], [[Miguel Gimenez Igualada]], [[Adolf Brand]] and [[Lev Chernyi]], among others.

=== Post-classical and contemporary ===
{{main|Contemporary anarchism}}
[[File:Jarach and Zerzan.JPG|thumb|[[Lawrence Jarach]] (left) and [[John Zerzan]] (right), two prominent [[Contemporary anarchism|contemporary anarchist]] authors, with Zerzan being a prominent voice within [[anarcho-primitivism]] and Jarach a noted advocate of [[post-left anarchy]]]]
Anarchist principles undergird contemporary radical social movements of the left. Interest in the anarchist movement developed alongside momentum in the [[anti-globalization movement]],{{sfn|Evren|2011|p=1}} whose leading activist networks were anarchist in orientation.{{sfn|Evren|2011|p=2}} As the movement shaped 21st century radicalism, wider embrace of anarchist principles signaled a revival of interest.{{sfn|Evren|2011|p=2}} Contemporary news coverage which emphasizes [[black bloc]] demonstrations has reinforced anarchism's historical association with chaos and violence, though its publicity has also led more scholars to engage with the anarchist movement.{{sfn|Evren|2011|p=1}} Anarchism continues to generate many philosophies and movements, at times eclectic, drawing upon various sources and [[Syncretic politics|syncretic]], combining disparate concepts to create new philosophical approaches.{{sfn|Perlin|1979}}

Anticapitalism stays prominent within contemporary anarchism, continuing the tradition of classical anarchism.{{sfn|Williams|2017|p=4}}

[[Insurrectionary anarchism]] is a revolutionary theory, practice and tendency within the anarchist movement which emphasises [[insurrection]] within anarchist practice. Critical of formal organisations such as [[labour unions]] and federations that are based on a political programme and periodic congresses, insurrectionary anarchists instead advocate informal organisation and small [[affinity group]] based organisation as well as putting value in attack, permanent [[class conflict]] and a refusal to negotiate or compromise with class enemies.

[[Green anarchism]], or [[eco-anarchism]], is a school of thought within anarchism that emphasises environmental issues,{{sfnm|1a1=Pepper|1y=1996|1p=44|2a1=Adams|2y=2001|2p=130}} with an important precedent in anarcho-naturism{{sfnm|1a1=Díez|1y=2006|2a1=Ortega|2y=2003}} and whose main contemporary currents are anarcho-primitivism and [[Social ecology (theory)|social ecology]]. Writing from a green anarchist perspective, [[John Zerzan]] attributes the ills of today's social degradation to technology and the birth of agricultural civilization.{{sfn|Zerzan|2002}} While [[Layla AbdelRahim]] argues that &quot;the shift in human consciousness was also a shift in human subsistence strategies, whereby some human animals reinvented their narrative to center murder and predation and thereby institutionalize violence&quot;.{{sfn|AbdelRahim|2015|p=8}} According to AbdelRahim, civilization was the result of the human development of technologies and grammar for predatory economics. Language and literacy, she claims, are some of these technologies.{{sfnm|1a1=AbdelRahim|1y=2013|2a1=AbdelRahim|2y=2015}}

[[Anarcho-pacifism]] is a tendency that rejects violence in the struggle for social change (see [[non-violence]]).{{sfn|Woodcock|1962}} It developed mostly in the Netherlands, Britain and the United States before and during the Second World War.{{sfn|Woodcock|1962}} Christian anarchism is a [[Christian movement|movement]] in [[political theology]] that combines anarchism and Christianity.{{sfn|Christoyannopoulos|2010|pp=2–4}} Its main proponents included [[Leo Tolstoy]], Dorothy Day, Ammon Hennacy and [[Jacques Ellul]].

[[Religious anarchism]] refers to a set of related anarchist ideologies that are inspired by the teachings of [[religion]]s. While many anarchists have traditionally been sceptical of and opposed to [[organized religion]], many different religions have served as inspiration for religious forms of anarchism, most notably [[Christianity]] as [[Christian anarchism|Christian anarchists]] believe that biblical teachings give credence to anarchist philosophy. Other examples include [[Buddhist anarchism]], [[Jewish anarchism]] and most recently [[Neopaganism]].

[[Synthesis anarchism]] is a form of anarchism that tries to join anarchists of different tendencies under the principles of anarchism without adjectives. In the 1920s, this form found as its main proponents the [[anarcho-communists]] [[Voline]] and [[Sébastien Faure]]. It is the main principle behind the anarchist federations grouped around the contemporary global [[International of Anarchist Federations]].{{sfn|The Anarchist FAQ Editorial Collective|2017|loc=J.3 What kinds of organisation do anarchists build?}}{{bcn|date=March 2019}}

[[Platformism]] is a tendency within the wider anarchist movement based on the organisational theories in the tradition of Dielo Truda's ''Organisational Platform of the General Union of Anarchists (Draft)''.{{sfn|Dielo Trouda|2006}} The document was based on the experiences of [[Anarchism in Russia|Russian anarchists]] in the 1917 [[October Revolution]] which led eventually to the victory of the [[Bolsheviks]] over the anarchists and other groups. The ''Platform'' attempted to address and explain the anarchist movement's failures during the [[Russian Revolution]].

[[Post-left anarchy]] is a recent current in anarchist thought that promotes a critique of anarchism's relationship to traditional [[left-wing politics]]. Some post-leftists seek to escape the confines of [[ideology]] in general also presenting a critique of organisations and [[morality]]. Influenced by the work of Max Stirner and by the Marxist [[Situationist International]], post-left anarchy is marked by a focus on social insurrection and a rejection of leftist social organisation.{{sfn|Macphee|2007|loc=Introduction}}

[[Post-anarchism]] is a theoretical move towards a synthesis of classical anarchist theory and [[poststructuralist]] thought, drawing from diverse ideas including post-left anarchy, [[postmodernism]], [[autonomism]], [[postcolonialism]] and the [[Situationist International]].

[[Queer anarchism]] is a form of [[socialism]] which suggests anarchism as a solution to the issues faced by the [[LGBT community]], mainly [[heteronormativity]], [[homophobia]], [[transphobia]] and [[biphobia]]. It arose during the late 20th century based on the work of [[Michel Foucault]]'s ''[[The History of Sexuality]]'' (1976).

[[Left-wing market anarchism]] strongly affirm the [[classical liberal]] ideas of [[self-ownership]] and [[free market]]s while maintaining that taken to their logical conclusions these ideas support strongly [[anti-capitalist]], [[Anti-corporatism|anti-corporatist]], [[Social hierarchies|anti-hierarchical]] and [[Labour movement|pro-labour]] positions in economics; [[anti-imperialism]] in foreign policy; and thoroughly radical views regarding such cultural issues as gender, sexuality and race.

[[Anarcho-capitalism]] advocates the elimination of the state in favour of self-ownership in a free market.{{sfnm|1a1=Hamowy|1y=2008|1pp=10–12, 195|2a1=Stringham|2y=2017|2p=51}} Anarcho-capitalism developed from radical American anti-state [[Libertarianism in the United States|libertarianism]] and [[Individualist anarchism in the United States|individualist anarchism]],{{sfn|Outhwaite|2008|p=14}} drawing from [[Austrian School]] economics, study of [[law and economics]] and [[public choice theory]].{{sfn|Stringham|2005}} There is a strong current within anarchism which believes that anarcho-capitalism cannot be considered a part of the anarchist movement due to the fact that anarchism has historically been an anti-capitalist movement and for definitional reasons which see anarchism as [[Anarchism and capitalism|incompatible]] with capitalist forms.{{r|Capitalism}}

[[Anarcho-transhumanism]] is a recently new branch of anarchism that takes traditional and modern anarchism, typically drawing from [[anarcho-syndicalism]], [[left-libertarianism]], or [[Libertarian socialist|libertarian socialism]], and combines it with [[transhumanism]] and [[post-humanism]]. It can be described as a &quot;liberal democratic revolution, at its core the idea that people are happiest when they have rational control over their lives. Reason, science, and technology provide one kind of control, slowly freeing us from ignorance, toil, pain, disease and limited lifespans (aging)&quot;. Some anarcho-transhumanists might also follow [[technogaianism]].{{cn|date=March 2019}}
&lt;!-- If you are looking to extend this section, please add the content to the proper sub-article [[anarchist schools of thought]] instead. --&gt;

==== Anarcha-feminism ====
{{main|Anarcha-feminism}}
[[Anarcha-feminism]], also called [[anarchist feminism]] and [[anarcho-feminism]], combines anarchism with [[feminism]]. It generally views [[patriarchy]] as a manifestation of involuntary coercive hierarchy that should be replaced by [[decentralised]] free association. Anarcha-feminists believe that the struggle against patriarchy is an essential part of [[class struggle]] and the anarchist struggle against the state. In essence, the philosophy sees anarchist struggle as a necessary component of feminist struggle and vice versa. Anarcha-feminists espoused to a detailed analysis of patriarchy and claim that oppression has its roots to social norms.{{sfn|Kowal|2019|p=275}}

Anarcha-feminism began with the late 19th-century writings of early feminist anarchists such as [[Emma Goldman]] and [[Voltairine de Cleyre]].{{sfn|Marshall|1993|p=556}} [[Mujeres Libres]] was an anarchist women's organisation in Spain that aimed to empower working class women, based on the idea of a double struggle for [[Feminist movement|women's liberation]] and social revolution and argued that the two objectives were equally important and should be pursued in parallel. In order to gain mutual support, they created networks of women anarchists.{{sfn|Kowal|2019|p=271}} The second wave of anarcha-feminism arose in the 1960s.{{sfn|Marshall|1993|pp=672–673}}

== Internal issues and debates ==
{{main|Issues in anarchism}}
&lt;!-- In the interest of restricting article length, please limit this section to two or three short paragraphs and add any substantial information to the main Issues in anarchism article. Thank you. --&gt;
As anarchism is a [[philosophy]] that embodies many diverse attitudes, tendencies and schools of thought and as such disagreement over questions of values, ideology and tactics is common, its diversity has led to widely different use of identical terms among different anarchist traditions which has led to many [[definitional concerns in anarchist theory]]. For instance, the compatibility of [[Anarchism and capitalism|capitalism]],{{sfn|Honderich|1995|p=31}} [[Anarchism and nationalism|nationalism]] and [[Anarchism and religion|religion]] with anarchism is widely disputed. Similarly, anarchism enjoys complex relationships with ideologies such as [[Anarchism and Marxism|Marxism]], [[Issues in anarchism#Communism|communism]], [[collectivism]] and [[trade unionism]]. Anarchists may be motivated by [[humanism]], [[God|divine authority]], [[enlightened self-interest]], [[Veganarchism|veganism]], or any number of alternative ethical doctrines. Phenomena such as [[civilisation]], [[technology]] (e.g. within [[anarcho-primitivism]]) and the [[Issues in anarchism#Participation in statist democracy|democratic process]] may be sharply criticised within some anarchist tendencies and simultaneously lauded in others. On a tactical level, [[propaganda of the deed]] was a tactic used by anarchists in the 19th century (e.g. the [[nihilist movement]]), with some contemporary anarchists espousing alternative direct action methods such as [[nonviolence]], [[counter-economics]] and [[Crypto-anarchism|anti-state cryptography]] to bring about an anarchist society. About the scope of an anarchist society, some anarchists advocate a global one while others do so by local ones.{{sfn|Trevijano|2001|p=57}}
{{clear}}

== Topics of interest ==
Intersecting and overlapping between various schools of thought, certain topics of interest and internal disputes have proven perennial within anarchist theory.

=== Anarchism and free love ===
{{main|Free love}}
{{see also|Anarchism and issues related to love and sex|Queer anarchism}}
[[File:Emilearmand01.jpg|thumb|upright|[[Individualist anarchism in France|French individualist anarchist]] [[Émile Armand]] propounded the virtues of [[free love]] in the [[Anarchism in France|Parisian anarchist milieu]] of the early 20th century]]
An important current within anarchism is [[free love]].{{sfn|McElroy|1996}} In Europe, the main propagandist of free love within individualist anarchism was Emile Armand. He proposed the concept of ''la camaraderie amoureuse'' to speak of free love as the possibility of voluntary sexual encounter between consenting adults. He was also a consistent proponent of [[polyamory]].{{sfn|Ronsin|2000}} In Germany, the [[Stirnerism|Stirnerists]] Adolf Brand and John Henry Mackay were pioneering campaigners for the acceptance of male [[bisexuality]] and [[homosexuality]]. More recently, the British anarcho-pacifist Alex Comfort gained notoriety during the [[sexual revolution]] for writing the bestseller sex manual ''[[The Joy of Sex]]''. The issue of free love has a dedicated treatment in the work of French anarcho-[[hedonist]] philosopher [[Michel Onfray]] in such works as ''Théorie du corps amoureux. Pour une érotique solaire'' (2000) and ''L'invention du plaisir. Fragments cyréaniques'' (2002).

=== Anarchism and education ===
{{main|Anarchism and education}}
[[File:Francisco Ferrer Guardia.jpg|thumb|left|upright|[[Francesc Ferrer i Guàrdia]], [[Anarchism in Spain|Catalan anarchist]] pedagogue and [[Freethought|free thinker]]]]
English anarchist William Godwin considered education an important aspect. He was against state education as he considered those schools as a way of the state to replicate privileges of the ruling class.{{sfn|Suissa|2019|p=514}} Godwin thought that education was the way to change the world. In his ''[[Political Justice]]'', he criticises state sponsored schooling and advocates for child's protection from coercion.{{sfn|Marshall|1993|p=197}} Max Stirner wrote in 1842 a long essay on education called ''[[The False Principle of our Education]]'' in which Stirner was advocating for child's autonomy.{{sfnm|1a1=Suissa|1y=2019|1p=521|2a1=Marshall|2y=1993|2p=222}}

In 1901, Catalan anarchist and free thinker [[Francisco Ferrer|Francesc Ferrer i Guàrdia]] established [[Ferrer movement|modern]] or [[Progressive education|progressive schools]] in Barcelona in defiance of an educational system controlled by the Catholic Church.{{sfn|Fidler|1985|pp=103–132}} Ferrer's approach was secular, rejecting both the state and church involvement in the educational process and gave pupils plenty of autonomy (i.e. on setting the curriculum). Ferrer was aiming to educate the working class. The school closed after constant harassment by the state and Ferrer was later on arrested.{{sfnm|1a1=Bookchin|1y=1998|1p=115|2a1=Suissa|2y=2019|2pp=511–514}} Ferrer's ideas generally formed the inspiration for a series of [[Modern School (United States)|modern schools]] in the United States,{{sfn|Fidler|1985|pp=103–132}}

Russian Christian anarchist Leo Tolstoy established a school for peasant children on his estate.{{sfn|Hern|2010}} Tolstoy's educational experiments were short-lived due to harassment by the Tsarist secret police.{{sfn|Wilson|2001|p=xxi}} Tolstoy established a conceptual difference between education and culture.{{sfn|Hern|2010}} He thought that &quot;[e]ducation is the tendency of one man to make another just like himself. [...] Education is culture under restraint, culture is free. [Education is] when the teaching is forced upon the pupil, and when then instruction is exclusive, that is when only those subjects are taught which the educator regards as necessary&quot;.{{sfn|Hern|2010}} For him, &quot;without compulsion, education was transformed into culture&quot;.{{sfn|Hern|2010}}

A more recent libertarian tradition on education is that of [[unschooling]] and the [[anarchist free school|free school]] in which child-led activity replaces pedagogic approaches. Experiments in Germany led to [[A. S. Neill]] founding what became [[Summerhill School]] in 1921.{{sfn|Purkis|2004}} Summerhill is often cited as an example of anarchism in practice.{{sfn|Vincent|2010|p=129}} However, although Summerhill and other free schools are radically libertarian, they differ in principle from those of Ferrer by not advocating an overtly political class struggle-approach.{{sfn|Suissa|2007}} In addition to organising schools according to libertarian principles, anarchists have also questioned the concept of schooling per se. The term [[deschooling]] was popularised by [[Ivan Illich]], who argued that the school as an institution is dysfunctional for self-determined learning and serves the creation of a consumer society instead.{{sfn|Illich|1971}}

=== Anarchism and the state ===
&lt;!-- Important! Strive to explain how anarchists perceive authority and oppression and why they reject them. Jun (2019), p. 41. --&gt;
Objection to the state and its institutions is ''[[sine qua non]]'' of anarchism.{{sfn|Carter|1971|p=14}} Anarchists consider the government as a tool of domination and it is illegitimate regardless of political tendencies. Instead of people being able to control the aspects of their life, major decisions are taken by a small elite. Authority ultimately rests solely on power regardless if it is [[Open government|open]] or transparent as it still has the ability to coerce people. Another anarchist argument against states is that some people constituting a government, even the most altruistic among officials, will unavoidably seek to gain more power, leading to corruption. Anarchists consider the argument that the state is the collective will of people as a fairy tale since the ruling class is distinct from the rest of the society.{{sfn|Jun|2019|pp=32–38}}

[[File:Gadewar.jpg|thumb|Which forms of violence, if any, are [[Anarchism and violence|consistent with anarchist values]] is a controversial subject among anarchists]]

=== Anarchism and violence ===
{{main|Anarchism and violence}}
Anarchist perspectives towards violence have always been perplexed and controversial.{{sfn|Carter|1978|p=320}} On one hand, anarcho-pacifists point out the unity of means and ends.{{sfn|Fiala|2017}} On the other hand, other groups of anarchist are for direct action that can include sabotage or even terrorism. [[Emma Goldman]] and [[Errico Malatesta]], who were proponents of limited use of violence, were arguing that violence is merely a reaction to state violence as a [[necessary evil]]. Peace activist and anarchist [[April Carter]] argues that violence is incompatible with anarchism because it is mostly associated with the state and authority as violence is immanent to the state. As the state's capability to exercise violence is colossal nowadays, a rebellion or civil war would probably end in another authoritarian institute.{{sfn|Carter|1978|pp=320–325}}

== Anarchist strategies and tactics ==

Anarchist tactics vary considerably. A broad categorization would be the preference of revolutionary tactics to destroy oppressive States and institutions or aiming to change society through evolutionary means. Revolutionary methods can take violent form as they did in past insurgencies (i.e., in Spain, Mexico, Russia) or during violent protests by militant protestors such as the [[black bloc]], who are generally much less violent than revolutionary movements a century ago. Anarchists also commonly employ [[direct action]], which can take the form of disrupting and protesting against unjust hierarchies, or the form of self-managing their lives through the creation of counterinstitutions such as communes and non-hierarchical collectives.{{sfn|Williams|2017|pp=4-5}} Often decision-making is handled in an anti-authoritarian way, with everyone having equal say in each decision, an approach known as [[Horizontalidad|horizontalism]]. Another aspect of anarchist tactics is their aim to strengthen social bonds through common actions.{{sfn|Williams|2019|pp=109-217}}

Reclaiming public space by anarchists is another method of creating social spaces and creating squats in order to organise themselves. During important events such as protests, when spaces are being occupied, they are often called 
&quot;[[Temporary Autonomous Zone]]s&quot; (TAZ).{{sfn|Williams|2017|pp=5-6}}

== Criticisms ==
Moral and pragmatic criticism of anarchism includes allegations of utopianism, tacit authoritarianism and vandalism towards feats of civilization.

=== Allegation of utopianism ===
Anarchism is evaluated as unfeasible or [[utopian]] by its critics, often in general and formal debate. European history professor Carl Landauer argued that social anarchism is unrealistic and that government is a &quot;lesser evil&quot; than a society without &quot;repressive force&quot;. He also argued that &quot;ill intentions will cease if repressive force disappears&quot; is an &quot;absurdity&quot;.{{sfn|Landauer|1959}} However, ''[[An Anarchist FAQ]]'' states the following: &quot;Anarchy is not a utopia, [and] anarchists make no such claims about human perfection. [...] Remaining disputes would be solved by reasonable methods, for example, the use of juries, mutual third parties, or community and workplace assemblies&quot;. It also states that &quot;some sort of 'court' system would still be necessary to deal with the remaining crimes and to adjudicate disputes between citizens&quot;.{{sfnm|1a1=The Anarchist FAQ Editorial Collective|1y=2017|1loc=A.2.16 Does anarchism require &quot;perfect&quot; people to work?|2a1=The Anarchist FAQ Editorial Collective|2y=2017|2loc=I.5.8 What about crime?}}

=== Tacit authoritarianism ===
The anarchist tendency known as [[platformism]] has been criticized by [[Situationist International|Situationists]],{{sfn|Debord|1993|loc=Paragraph 91}} [[Insurrectionary anarchism|insurrectionaries]], [[Synthesis anarchism|synthesis anarchists]] and others of preserving tacitly statist, authoritarian or bureaucratic tendencies.{{citation needed|date=March 2019}}

=== Anarchism and civilization ===
In his essay ''On Authority'', [[Friedrich Engels]] claimed that radical [[decentralization]] promoted by anarchists would destroy modern industrial civilization, citing an example of [[railway]]s:{{sfn|Engels|1978}} {{quote|Here too the co-operation of an infinite number of individuals is absolutely necessary, and this co-operation must be practised during precisely fixed hours so that no accidents may happen. Here, too, the first condition of the job is a dominant will that settles all subordinate questions, whether this will is represented by a single delegate or a committee charged with the execution of the resolutions of the majority of persona interested. In either case there is a very pronounced authority. Moreover, what would happen to the first train dispatched if the authority of the railway employees over the Hon. passengers were abolished?}}

In the end, it is argued that authority in any form is a natural occurrence which should not be abolished.{{sfn|Goodwin|2014}}

== List of anarchist societies ==
{{see also|List of anarchist communities}}
* [[Fejuve|Federation of Neighborhood Councils-El Alto]] (Fejuve; 1979–present){{sfn|Gelderloss|2010}}
* [[Popular Indigenous Council of Oaxaca &quot;Ricardo Flores Magón&quot;]] (CIPO-RFM; 1980s–present){{sfn|Denham|2008}}
* [[Landless Workers' Movement]] (MST; 1982–present){{sfn|Gelderloss|2010}}
* [[Rebel Zapatista Autonomous Municipalities]] (MANEZ; 1994–present){{sfn|Zibechi|2012|p=132}}
* [[Barbacha]] (2001–present)
* [[Villa de Zaachila]] (2006–present)
* [[Cherán|Cheran]] (2011–present)
* [[Democratic Federation of Northern Syria]] (Rojava; 2013–present)

== See also ==
* [[:Category:Anarchism by country|Anarchism by country]]
* [[Governance without government]]
* [[Libertarian socialism]]
* [[List of political ideologies#Anarchism|List of anarchist political ideologies]]
* {{Portal-inline|size=tiny|Anarchism}}

; Foundational texts of anarchism&lt;!-- Source: McLaughlin, 2007. --&gt;
* ''[[Enquiry Concerning Political Justice]]'' (1793) 
* ''[[What is Property?]] (1840) 
* ''[[The Ego and Its Own]]'' (1844)

== References ==
{{reflist|refs=
&lt;ref name=Capitalism&gt;{{harvnb|Meltzer|2000|p=50}}: &quot;The philosophy of &quot;anarcho-capitalism&quot; dreamed up by the &quot;libertarian&quot; [[New Right]], has nothing to do with Anarchism as known by the Anarchist movement proper.&quot;;
{{harvnb|Marshall|1993|p=565}}: &quot;In fact, few anarchists would accept the 'anarcho-capitalists' into the anarchist camp since they do not share a concern for economic equality and social justice, Their self-interested, calculating market men would be incapable of practising voluntary co-operation and mutual aid. Anarcho-capitalists, even if they do reject the State, might therefore best be called right-wing libertarians rather than anarchists.&quot;;
{{harvnb|Newman|2010|p=53}}: &quot;It is important to distinguish between anarchism and certain strands of right-wing libertarianism which at times go by the same name (for example, Murray Rothbard's anarcho-capitalism).&quot;;
{{harvnb|Goodway|2006|p=4}}: &quot;'Libertarian' and 'libertarianism' are frequently employed by anarchists as synonyms for 'anarchist' and 'anarchism', largely as an attempt to distance themselves from the negative connotations of 'anarchy' and its derivatives. The situation has been vastly complicated in recent decades with the rise of anarcho-capitalism, 'minimal statism' and an extreme right-wing laissez-faire philosophy advocated by such theorists as Murray Rothbard and Robert Nozick and their adoption of the words 'libertarian' and 'libertarianism'. It has therefore now become necessary to distinguish between their right libertarianism and the left libertarianism of the anarchist tradition&quot;.&lt;/ref&gt;
}}
{{refbegin}}
{{refend}}

== Sources ==
=== Primary ===
{{refbegin|30em|indent=yes}}
* {{cite book |last=Bakunin |first=Mikhail Aleksandrovich |authorlink=Mikhail Bakunin |title=Statism and Anarchy |year=1990 |orig-year=1873 |publisher=Cambridge University Press |location=Cambridge |series=Cambridge Texts in the History of Political Thought |translator-last=Shatz |translator-first=Marshall |isbn=978-0-521-36182-8 |oclc=20826465 |lccn=89077393 |doi=10.1017/CBO9781139168083  |ref=harv}}
* {{cite wikisource |last=Berkman |first=Alexander |author-link=Alexander Berkman |title=Now and After: The ABC of Communist Anarchism |year=1929 |publisher=Vanguard Press |location=New York |oclc=529173 |lccn=29022523 |ref=harv}}
* {{cite book |last=Engels |first=Fredrick |author-link=Frederick Engels |editor-last=Tucker |editor-first=Robert C. |title=The Marx-Engels reader |edition=2nd |chapter=On Authority |year=1978 |orig-year=1874 |publisher=Norton |location=New York |isbn=978-0-393-05684-6 |oclc=318414641 |lccn=77016635 |ref=harv |chapter-url=https://www.marxists.org/archive/marx/works/1872/10/authority.htm |access-date=2019-03-18 |via=Marxists Internet Archive }}
* {{cite book |last=Godwin |first=William |author-link=William Godwin |title=Enquiry Concerning Political Justice and its Influence on Modern Morals and Manners |year=1798 |orig-year=1793 |edition=3rd, corrected |publisher=G.G. and J. Robinson |location=London |oclc=6978206 |ref=harv |url=https://catalog.hathitrust.org/Record/008421359 |via=Hathi Trust}}
* {{cite book |last=Guillaume |first=James |authorlink=James Guillaume |editor-last=Dolgoff |editor-first=Sam  |title=Bakunin on Anarchy |chapter=Ideas on Social Organization |year=1972 |orig-year=1876 |publisher=A.A. Knopf |location=New York |isbn=978-0-394-41601-4 |oclc=267856 |lccn=79136351 |chapter-url=https://www.marxists.org/reference/archive/guillaume/works/ideas.htm |access-date=2019-03-18 |via=Marxists Internet Archive |ref=harv}} 
* {{cite book |author=Dielo Trouda |authorlink=Dielo Truda |title=Organizational Platform of the General Union of Anarchists (Draft) |year=2006 |origyear=1926 
|translator-last=McNab |translator-first=Nestor |publisher=The Nestor Makhno Archive 
|url=http://www.nestormakhno.info/english/newplatform/org_plat.htm |access-date=2019-03-18 |ref=harv}}
* {{cite book|last=Greene |first=William Batchelder |title=Socialistic, Communistic, Mutualistic and Financial Fragments |year=1875 |section=Communism versus Mutualism |publisher=Lee and Shepard |location=Boston |oclc=2567184 |lccn=08033079 |url=https://catalog.hathitrust.org/api/volumes/oclc/2567184.html |ref=harv}}  
* {{cite book|last=Kropotkin |first=Pëtr |authorlink=Peter Kropotkin |title=The Conquest of Bread|orig-year=1892|publisher=AK Press |location=Edinburgh |year=2007 |isbn=978-1-904859-10-9|ref=harv|title-link=The Conquest of Bread }}
* {{cite book|last=Kropotkin |first=Pëtr |authorlink=Peter Kropotkin |title=Anarchism: A Collection of Revolutionary Writings|publisher=Courier Dover Publications|year=2002|page=5|isbn=978-0-486-41955-8 |ref=harv}}
* {{cite book|last=Rae|first=John |title=Contemporary Socialism|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=9ZASAAAAIAAJ|year=1901|publisher=C. Scribner's sons|ref=harv}}
* {{cite book|last=Rocker|first= Rudolf|authorlink= Rudolf Rocker| title = Anarcho-Syndicalism: Theory and Practice|year=2004|orig-year=1947|publisher = AK Press|ref=harv|title-link= Anarcho-Syndicalism (book)}}
* {{cite book|author=The Anarchist FAQ Editorial Collective |title = An Anarchist FAQ |year=2017 |ref=harv|title-link = An Anarchist FAQ }}
{{refend}}

=== Secondary ===
{{refbegin|30em|indent=yes}}
* {{cite book | last = AbdelRahim | first = Layla | authorlink=Layla AbdelRahim | title = Wild Children – Domesticated Dreams: Civilization and the Birth of Education | publisher = Fernwood | location = Halifax | year = 2013 | isbn = 978-1-55266-548-0|ref=harv}}
* {{cite book | last = AbdelRahim | first = Layla | authorlink=Layla AbdelRahim | title = Children's Literature, Domestication, and Social Foundation: Narratives of Civilization and Wilderness | publisher = Routledge | location = New York | year = 2015 | isbn = 978-0-415-66110-2 |ref=harv}}
* {{cite book |last=Adams |first=Ian |title=Political Ideology Today |publisher=Manchester University Press |year=2001 |ref=harv}}
* {{Cite journal |last=Anderson|first=Benedict |author-link=Benedict Anderson |title=In the World-Shadow of Bismarck and Nobel |journal=[[New Left Review]] |volume=2 |issue=28 |pages=85–129 |year= 2004 |url=http://newleftreview.org/II/28/benedict-anderson-in-the-world-shadow-of-bismarck-and-nobel |access-date = 2016-01-07 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20151219130121/http://newleftreview.org/II/28/benedict-anderson-in-the-world-shadow-of-bismarck-and-nobel |archive-date=2015-12-19 |ref=harv}}
* {{cite book |last=Avrich |first=Paul |title=Anarchist Voices: An Oral History of Anarchism in America |year=1996|publisher=Princeton University Press |isbn=978-0-691-04494-1|ref=harv}}
* {{Cite book|last = Avrich |first = Paul |authorlink=Paul Avrich|title = The Russian Anarchists |publisher = [[AK Press]] |location = Stirling |year = 2006 |isbn = 978-1-904859-48-2 |ref =harv|title-link = The Russian Anarchists }}
* {{cite book|last= Bantman|first= Constance |chapter=The Era of Propaganda by the Deed|editor1-last=Levy|editor1-first=Carl |editor1-link=Carl Levy (political scientist)|editor2-last=Adams|editor2-first=Matthew S. |title=The Palgrave Handbook of Anarchism|year=2019|publisher=[[Springer Publishing]]|isbn=978-3-319-75620-2|ref=harv}}
* {{cite book|ref=harv|last=Bates|first=David|editor=Paul Wetherly|title=Political Ideologies|chapter-url=https://books.google.com/books?id=uXfJDgAAQBAJ&amp;pg=PA128|year=2017|publisher=Oxford University Press|isbn=978-0-19-872785-9|chapter=Anarchism}}
* {{cite book |last=Bolloten |first=Burnett |author-link=Burnett Bolloten |title=The Spanish Civil War: Revolution and Counterrevolution |publisher=University of North Carolina Press |year=1984 |isbn=978-0-8078-1906-7 |ref=harv}}
* {{cite book|last=Bookchin|first=Murray|authorlink=Murray Bookchin|title=The Spanish Anarchists: The Heroic Years, 1868-1936|year=1998|publisher=AK Press|isbn=978-1-873176-04-7|ref=harv|title-link=The Spanish Anarchists: The Heroic Years, 1868-1936}}
* {{cite book |last=Bookchin |first=Murray |author-link=Murray Bookchin |title=To Remember Spain: The Anarchist and Syndicalist Revolution of 1936 |year=2009 |orig-year=1994 |url=http://www.theanarchistlibrary.org/HTML/Murray_Bookchin__To_Remember_Spain__The_Anarchist_and_Syndicalist_Revolution_of_1936.html |publisher=The Anarchist Library |ref=harv}} 
* {{cite book|last=Brooks|first=Frank H.|year=1994|title=The Individualist Anarchists: An Anthology of Liberty (1881–1908)|publisher= Transaction Publishers |isbn=978-1-56000-132-4|ref=harv}} 
* {{cite book|last=Carter|first=April |authorlink=April Carter|title=The Political Theory of Anarchism|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=3mlWPgAACAAJ|year=1971|publisher=Routledge|isbn=978-0-415-55593-7|ref=harv}}
* {{cite book|last=Carlson|first=Andrew|title=Anarchism in Germany|publisher=Scarecrow Press|year=1972|isbn=978-0-8108-0484-5|location=Metuchen|chapter-url=http://tmh.floonet.net/articles/carlson.html|chapter= Philosophical Egoism: German Antecedents
|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20131024210422/http://tmh.floonet.net/articles/carlson.html |archivedate=2013-10-24|ref=harv }}
* {{cite journal |last=Carter |first=April |title=Anarchism and violence |journal=Nomos |volume=19 |pages=320–340 |year=1978 |publisher=American Society for Political and Legal Philosophy |ref=harv |jstor=24219053}}
* {{cite book |editor1-last=Chaliand |editor1-first=Gerard |editor2-last=Blin |editor2-first=Arnaud |title = The History of Terrorism: From Antiquity to Al-Quaeda |publisher=University of California Press |location=Berkeley, Los Angeles, London |year=2007 |isbn=978-0-520-24709-3 |oclc=634891265 |ref=harv}}
* {{cite book |last=Christoyannopoulos |first=Alexandre |authorlink=Alexandre Christoyannopoulos |title=Christian Anarchism: A Political Commentary on the Gospel|year=2010 |publisher=Imprint Academic |location=Exeter |ref=harv}}
* {{cite book|last=Copleston|first=Frederick Charles|authorlink=Frederick Copleston|title=19th and 20th Century French Philosophy|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=rcR8rHqienwC&amp;pg=PA69|date=1 January 2003|publisher=A&amp;C Black|isbn=978-0-8264-6903-8|ref=harv}}
* {{cite book|last=Debord|first=Guy|authorlink=Guy Debord|year=1993|translator=Ken Knabb|title=Society of the Spectacle|publisher=Rebel Press|location=London|isbn=978-0-946061-12-9|title-link=Society of the Spectacle|ref=harv}}
* {{cite book|last=Denham|first=Diana|title=Teaching Rebellion: Stories from the Grassroots Mobilization in Oaxaca|publisher=PM Press|year=2008|ref=harv}}
* {{cite article |last=Díez |first=Xavier |title=La insumisión voluntaria: El anarquismo individualista español durante la Dictadura y la Segunda República (1923–1938) |date=April 2006 |url=http://www.acracia.org/1-23a58lainsumision.pdf |archive-url=https://www.webcitation.org/5zcwSjuqw?url=http://www.acracia.org/1-23a58lainsumision.pdf |archive-date=22 June 2011 |format=pdf |ref=harv}}
* {{cite book|last1=Díez|first1=Xavier|url=http://libros.metabiblioteca.org/handle/001/450|title=El anarquismo individualista en España 1923–1938|year=2007|publisher=Virus Editorial|isbn=978-84-96044-87-6|location=Barcelona|ref=harv}}
* {{cite book |last=Dirlik |first=Arif |title=Anarchism in the Chinese Revolution |publisher=University of California Press |location=Berkeley |year=1991 |isbn=978-0-520-07297-8 |ref=harv}}
* {{cite book |last=Dodson |first=Edward |title=The Discovery of First Principles |volume=2 |publisher=Authorhouse |year=2002 |isbn=978-0-595-24912-1 |ref=harv}}
* {{cite book |last=Esenwein|first=George Richard|title=Anarchist Ideology and the Working-class Movement in Spain, 1868-1898|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=13Hck24xgHUC|date=1 January 1989|publisher=University of California Press|isbn=978-0-520-06398-3|ref=harv}}
* {{cite book| last =Everhart|first = Robert B|title= The Public School Monopoly: A Critical Analysis of Education and the State in American Society|publisher = Pacific Institute for Public Policy Research|year = 1982|p= 115|ref=harv}}
* {{Cite book |last=Evren |first=Süreyyya |authorlink=Süreyyya Evren |chapter=How New Anarchism Changed the World (of Opposition) after Seattle and Gave Birth to Post-Anarchism |pages=1–19 |editor-last1=Rousselle |editor-first1=Duane |editor-last2=Evren |editor-first2=Süreyyya |title=Post-Anarchism: A Reader |date=2011 |isbn=978-0-7453-3086-0 |publisher=[[Pluto Press]] |ref=harv }}
* {{cite book |last=Fernández |first=Frank |title=Cuban Anarchism: The History of A Movement |year=2009 |orig-year=2001 |publisher=Sharp Press |url=http://www.theanarchistlibrary.org/HTML/Frank_Fernandez__Cuban_Anarchism__The_History_of_A_Movement.html |ref=harv}}
*{{cite journal |last=Fidler |first =Geoffrey C. |year= 1985 |title=The Escuela Moderna Movement of Francisco Ferrer: &quot;Por la Verdad y la Justicia&quot; |journal=History of Education Quarterly |volume=25 |issue=1/2 |pages=103–132   |doi=10.2307/368893 |jstor=368893 |ref=harv}}
* {{cite book |last=Flint |date=2009 |first=Colin |section=Anarchism |editor=Derek Gregory |editor2=Ron Johnston |editor3=Geraldine Pratt |editor4=Michael Watts |editor5=Sarah Whatmore |title=The Dictionary of Human Geography |edition=5th |url=http://www.univpgri-palembang.ac.id/perpus-fkip/Perpustakaan/Geography/Kamus%20Geografi/Kamus%20Geografi%20Manusia.pdf |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20150523054520/http://www.univpgri-palembang.ac.id/perpus-fkip/Perpustakaan/Geography/Kamus%20Geografi/Kamus%20Geografi%20Manusia.pdf |archivedate=23 May 2015 |publisher=Wiley-Blackwell |publicationdate=23 April 2009 |isbn=978-1-4051-3287-9 |editorlink=Derek Gregory |editorlink2=Ron Johnston (geographer) |editorlink4=Michael Watts |editorlink5=Sarah Whatmore (geographer) |ref = harv }}
* {{cite journal|last = Fowler|first = R.B.|title=The Anarchist Tradition of Political Thought|year=1972|journal=Western Political Quarterly |volume=25|issue=4|pages=738–752|doi=10.2307/446800|jstor=446800|ref=harv}}
* {{cite book|last1= Jun|first1= Nathan|chapter=The State|editor1-last=Levy|editor1-first=Carl |editor1-link=Carl Levy (political scientist)|editor2-last=Adams|editor2-first=Matthew S. |title=The Palgrave Handbook of Anarchism|year=2019|publisher=[[Springer Publishing]]|isbn=978-3-319-75620-2|ref=harv}}
* {{cite journal|last=Gabardi| first=Wayne|title =The American Political Science Review|year= 1986|journal =The American Political Science Review|volume=80|issue= 1| pages=300–302|doi= 10.2307/1957102|jstor=446800|ref=harv}}
* {{cite book|last=Gelderloss|first =Peter|title=Anarchy Works|publisher=Ardent Press|year=2010|isbn=978-1-62049-020-4|location=|pages=|url = https://theanarchistlibrary.org/library/peter-gelderloos-anarchy-works|ref=harv}}
* {{cite book|last=Goodway|first= David|authorlink = David Goodway|title= Anarchist Seeds Beneath the Snow|publisher = Liverpool Press|year= 2006|isbn =978-1-84631-025-6|ref=harv}}
* {{cite book|last=Goodwin|first= Barbara|year=2014|title =Using Political Ideas, Sixth edition|publisher= John Wiley and Sons, Inc.|location = Hoboken, New Jersey|ref=harv}}
* {{cite book|last=Graham|first=Robert|title=Anarchism: a Documentary History of Libertarian Ideas: from Anarchy to Anarchism|publisher=Black Rose Books|location=Montréal|year=2005|isbn=978-1-55164-250-5|authorlink=Robert Graham (historian)|url=http://robertgraham.wordpress.com/anarchism-a-documentary-history-of-libertarian-ideas-volume-one-from-anarchy-to-anarchism-300ce-1939/|access-date=5 March 2011|archive-url =https://web.archive.org/web/20101130131904/http://robertgraham.wordpress.com/anarchism-a-documentary-history-of-libertarian-ideas-volume-one-from-anarchy-to-anarchism-300ce-1939/|archive-date=30 November 2010|ref=harv}}
* {{cite book|last=Graham|first=Robert |authorlink=Robert Graham (historian)|title=We Do Not Fear Anarchy?We Invoke It: The First International and the Origins of the Anarchist Movement|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=71xkCgAAQBAJ|year =2015|publisher=AK Press|isbn=978-1-84935-212-3|ref=harv}}
* {{cite book|ref=harv|last1= Graham|first1= Robert|author-link1= Robert Graham (historian)|chapter=Anarchism and the First International|editor1-last=Levy|editor1-first=Carl |editor1-link=Carl Levy (political scientist)|editor2-last=Adams|editor2-first=Matthew S. |title=The Palgrave Handbook of Anarchism|chapter-url=https://books.google.com.cy/books/about/The_Palgrave_Handbook_of_Anarchism.html?id=SRyQswEACAAJ&amp;source=kp_book_description&amp;redir_esc=y|year =2019|publisher=Springer|isbn=978-3-319-75620-2}}
* {{cite book|last=Guerin|first=Daniel |authorlink=Daniel Guérin|title=Anarchism: from theory to practice|url=http://theanarchistlibrary.org/library/daniel-guerin-anarchism-from-theory-to-practice|year=1970|publisher=Monthly Review Press |ref = harv}}
* {{cite book|ref=harv|last1=Harrison|first1=Kevin |last2=Boyd|first2=Tony |title=Understanding Political Ideas and Movements|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=5qrJCgAAQBAJ|date=5 December 2003|publisher=Manchester University Press|isbn=978-0-7190-6151-6}}
* {{cite book |last=Hern |first=Matt |title=The Emergence of Compulsory Schooling and Anarchist Resistance |year=2010 |orig-year=2003 |publisher=The Anarchist Library |url=http://theanarchistlibrary.org/library/matt-hern-the-emergence-of-compulsory-schooling-and-anarchist-resistance |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20190301102015/http://theanarchistlibrary.org/library/matt-hern-the-emergence-of-compulsory-schooling-and-anarchist-resistance |archive-date=1 March 2019 |access-date=1 March 2019 |dead-url=no |ref=harv}}
* {{cite book|last=Heywood|first=Andrew |authorlink=Andrew Heywood|title=Political Ideologies: An Introduction|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=Sy8hDgAAQBAJ&amp;pg=PA146|edition=6th|date=16 February 2017|publisher=Macmillan International Higher Education|isbn=978-1-137-60604-4|ref=harv}}
* {{cite book|last=Honderich|first=Ted |title=The Oxford Companion to Philosophy|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=sI4YAAAAIAAJ|year=1995|publisher=Oxford University Press|isbn=978-0-19-866132-0|ref=harv}}
* {{cite article |last=Imrie |first=Doug |title=The Illegalists |year=1994 |work=Anarchy: a Journal Of Desire Armed |url=http://recollectionbooks.com/siml/library/illegalistsDougImrie.htm |deadurl=yes |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20150908072801/http://recollectionbooks.com/siml/library/illegalistsDougImrie.htm |archivedate=8 September 2015 |access-date=9 December 2010 |ref=harv}}
* {{cite book |last=Illich| first=Ivan |title=Deschooling Society |place= New York|publisher= Harper and Row| year= 1971| isbn= 978-0-06-012139-6|ref=harv}}
* {{cite book |last1=Isaacs |first1= Stuart |first2=Chris|last2= Sparks |date=2004-05-20 |title=Political Theorists in Context |url={{google books|rlGFAgAAQBAJ|plainurl=yes}} |publisher=Routledge  |isbn=978-0-415-20126-1|ref=harv}}
* {{cite book|title=The Anarchists|last=Joll|first=James|authorlink = James Joll|year=1964|publisher=Harvard University Press|isbn= 978-0-674-03642-0 |ref=harv}}
* {{cite journal|last= Kahn|first=Joseph|title=Anarchism, the Creed That Won't Stay Dead; The Spread of World Capitalism Resurrects a Long-Dormant Movement|year=2000|journal=[[The New York Times]]|issue=5 August|ref=harv}}
* {{cite book|last=Klosko|first=George |title=Political Obligations|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=ToHmfIj8d_gC|year=2005|publisher=Oxford University Press|isbn=978-0-19-955104-0|ref=harv}}
* {{cite book|last1= Kowal|first1= Donna M.|chapter=Anarcha-Feminism|editor1-last=Levy|editor1-first=Carl |editor1-link=Carl Levy (political scientist)|editor2-last=Adams|editor2-first=Matthew S. |title=The Palgrave Handbook of Anarchism|year=2019|publisher=[[Springer Publishing]]|isbn=978-3-319-75620-2|ref=harv}}
* {{cite book|last=Landauer|first=Carl|year =1959|title=European Socialism: A History of Ideas and Movements|ref=harv}}
* {{cite book|ref=harv|last= Laursen|first= Ole Birk|chapter=Anti-Imperialism|editor1-last=Levy|editor1-first=Carl |editor1-link=Carl Levy (political scientist)|editor2-last=Adams|editor2-first=Matthew S. |title=The Palgrave Handbook of Anarchism|chapter-url=https://books.google.com.cy/books/about/The_Palgrave_Handbook_of_Anarchism.html?id=SRyQswEACAAJ&amp;source=kp_book_description&amp;redir_esc=y|year=2019|publisher=Springer|isbn=978-3-319-75620-2}}
* {{cite journal | last=Levy | first=Carl | authorlink= Carl Levy (political scientist)|title=Social Histories of Anarchism | journal=Journal for the Study of Radicalism | volume=4 | issue=2 | date=2011-05-08 | issn=1930-1197 | doi=10.1353/jsr.2010.0003 | pages=1–44 | ref=harv }}
* {{cite book|last=Long|first=Roderick|editor1=Gerald F. Gaus|editor2=Fred D'Agostino|title=The Routledge Companion to Social and Political Philosophy|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=z7MzEHaJgKAC|year=2013|publisher=Routledge|isbn=978-0-415-87456-4|ref=harv}}
* {{cite book|last=Marshall|first=Peter|authorlink = Peter Marshall (author)|title=Demanding the Impossible: A History of Anarchism|year=1993 |publisher=PM Press|place=Oakland, CA|isbn=978-1-60486-064-1|ref = harv}}
* {{cite book|last=Macphee|first=Josh|title=Realizing the Impossible|chapter=Introduction|publisher=AK Press|location=Stirling|year=2007|isbn=978-1-904859-32-1|ref=harv}}
* {{cite book |last=Mayne |first=Alan James |url=https://books.google.com/?id=6MkTz6Rq7wUC&amp;pg=PA131&amp;dq=Communist+anarchism+believes+in+collective+ownership |title=From Politics Past to Politics Future: An Integrated Analysis of Current and Emergent Paradigms |year=1999 |publisher=Greenwood Publishing Group |access-date=20 September 2010|isbn=978-0-275-96151-0|ref=harv}}
* {{cite journal|last= McElroy|first= Wendy |date=1981 |title=Culture of Individualist Anarchism in Late 19th Century America |url=https://mises.org/journals/jls/5_3/5_3_4.pdf |journal=[[Journal of Libertarian Studies]] |volume=5 |issue=3 |pages=291–304 |accessdate=13 September 2014 |authorlink=Wendy McElroy|ref=harv }}
* {{cite web|last= McElroy|first= Wendy |year= 1996|url=http://www.ncc-1776.org/tle1996/le961210.html|title=The Free Love Movement and Radical Individualism |work=ncc-1776.org|accessdate=29 November 2009|ref=harv}}
* {{cite book |last=McLaughlin |year=2007 |first=Paul |title=Anarchism and Authority: A Philosophical Introduction to Classical Anarchism |url=https://we.riseup.net/assets/394498/paul-mclaughlin-anarchism-and-authority-a-philosophical-introduction-to-classical-anarchism-1.pdf |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20180804180522/https://we.riseup.net/assets/394498/paul-mclaughlin-anarchism-and-authority-a-philosophical-introduction-to-classical-anarchism-1.pdf |archivedate=4 August 2018 |publisher=[[Ashgate Publishing|Ashgate]] |place=Aldershot |publicationdate=2007-11-28 |isbn=978-0-7546-6196-2 |ref = harv }}
* {{cite book|last=Meltzer|first=Albert |authorlink=Albert Meltzer|title=Anarchism: Arguments for and Against|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=CJhCvx_Z0CAC|date=1 January 2000|publisher=AK Press|isbn=978-1-873176-57-3|ref=harv}}
* {{cite book|last =Morris |first= Brian |title=Bakunin: The Philosophy of Freedom|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=GJXy5eCpPawC|date=January 1993|publisher=Black Rose Books|isbn=978-1-895431-66-7|ref=harv}}
* {{cite book|ref=harv|last=Morris|first=Christopher W. |title=An Essay on the Modern State|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=uuyJ9Bw8w7QC |year= 2002|publisher=Cambridge University Press|isbn=978-0-521-52407-0}}
* {{cite journal |last = Moynihan|first = Colin|title=Book Fair Unites Anarchists. In Spirit, Anyway|year=2007|journal=New York Times|issue = 16 April|ref=harv}}
* {{cite book|ref=harv|last=Moya|first=Jose C|editor=Geoffroy de Laforcade|others=Kirwin R. Shaffer|title=In Defiance of Boundaries: Anarchism in Latin American History|chapter-url=https://books.google.com/books?id=ikt6AQAACAAJ|year=2015|publisher=[[University Press of Florida]]|isbn=978-0-8130-5138-3|chapter=Transference, culture, and critique The Circulation of Anarchist Ideas and Practices}}
* {{cite book|last=Nettlau|first=Max|authorlink=Max Nettlau|title=A Short History of Anarchism|year=1996|publisher=Freedom Press|isbn= 978-0-900384-89-9 |ref=harv}}
* {{cite book|last=Newman|first=Saul |title=The Politics of Postanarchism|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=SiqBiViUsOkC&amp;pg=PA43|year=2010|publisher=Edinburgh University Press|isbn=978-0-7486-3495-8|ref=harv}}
* {{cite book |last=Nomad |first=Max |contribution=The Anarchist Tradition |editor1-last=Drachkovitch |editor1-first=Milorad M. |title=Revolutionary Internationals 1864–1943 |publisher=Stanford University Press |page=88 |year=1966 |isbn=978-0-8047-0293-5 |ref=harv}}
* {{cite web |last=Ortega |first=Carlos |title=Anarchism – Nudism, Naturism |date=Winter 2003  |url=http://www.naturismo.org/adn/ediciones/2003/invierno/7e.html |website=Asociacion para el Desarrollo Naturista de la Comunidad de Madrid |ref=harv}}
* {{cite book |last=Ossar |first=Michael |date=1980 |title=Anarchism in the Dramas of Ernst Toller |publisher=SUNY Press |isbn=978-0-87395-393-1 |ref=harv}}
* {{cite book |last=Ostergaard |first=Geoffrey|section=Anarchism |editor=Thomas Bottomore |title=A Dictionary of Marxist Thought |edition=revised |url=https://gruppegrundrisse.files.wordpress.com/2012/06/bottomore-a-dictionary-of-marxist-thought.pdf|year =1991  |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20180804012806/https://gruppegrundrisse.files.wordpress.com/2012/06/bottomore-a-dictionary-of-marxist-thought.pdf |archivedate=8 August 2018 |publisher=Blackwell Publishing |p=21 |isbn=978-0-631-18082-1 |authorlink=Geoffrey Ostergaard |editorlink=Thomas Bottomore |ref=harv}}
* {{cite book|last=Ostergaard|first=Geoffrey |authorlink=Geoffrey Ostergaard|editor=William Outhwaite|title=The Blackwell Dictionary of Modern Social Thought|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=JJmdpqJwkwwC&amp;pg=PA14|year=2006|publisher=Blackwell Publishing Ltd|isbn=978-0-470-99901-1|ref=harv}}
* {{cite web |last=Ostergaard |first=Geoffrey |title=Resisting the Nation State. The pacifist and anarchist tradition |year=2009 |orig-year=1982 |publisher=The Anarchist Library |url=http://theanarchistlibrary.org/library/geoffrey-ostergaard-resisting-the-nation-state-the-pacifist-and-anarchist-tradition |ref=harv}}
* {{cite book|last=Parry|first=Richard |title=The Bonnot Gang|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=cXsWDa3oTI4C|year=1987|publisher=Rebel Press|isbn=978-0-946061-04-4|ref=harv}}
* {{cite article |last=Pengam |first=Alain |title=Anarchist-Communism |url=http://theanarchistlibrary.org/library/alain-pengam-anarchist-communism |publisher=The Anarchist Library |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20190301100728/http://theanarchistlibrary.org/library/alain-pengam-anarchist-communism |archive-date=1 March 2019 |access-date=1 March 2019 |dead-url=no |ref=harv}}
* {{cite book|last=Perlin|first=Terry M. |year=1979|title=Contemporary Anarchism|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=mppLKlwHx7oC|publisher=Transaction Publishers|isbn=978-1-4128-2033-2|ref=harv}}
* {{cite book|last=Pepper|first=David |title=Modern Environmentalism: An Introduction|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=PQOvkB7UoWgC&amp;pg=PA44|year=1996|publisher=Routledge|isbn=978-0-415-05745-5|ref=harv}}
* {{cite book|last=Pernicone|first=Nunzio |title=Italian Anarchism, 1864-1892|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=3ttgjwEACAAJ|year=2009|publisher=Princeton University Press|isbn=978-0-691-63268-1|ref=harv}}*{{cite book|ref=harv|last=Pierson|first=Christopher |title=Just Property: Enlightenment, Revolution, and History|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=7jvKDAAAQBAJ&amp;pg=PA187|year=2013|publisher=Oxford University Press|isbn=978-0-19-967329-2}}
* {{cite book | last = Purkis | first = Jon | title = Changing Anarchism | publisher = Manchester University Press | location = Manchester | year = 2004 | isbn = 978-0-7190-6694-8 |ref=harv}}
* {{cite book|ref=harv|last=Ramnath|first=Maia |editor1-last=Levy|editor1-first=Carl |editor1-link=Carl Levy (political scientist)|editor2-last=Adams|editor2-first=Matthew S.|title=The Palgrave Handbook of Anarchism|chapter-url=https://books.google.com.cy/books/about/The_Palgrave_Handbook_of_Anarchism.html?id=SRyQswEACAAJ&amp;source=kp_book_description&amp;redir_esc=y|year=2019|publisher=Springer|isbn=978-3-319-75620-2|chapter=Non-Western Anarchisms and Postcolonialism|authormask=|trans-title=|chapter-format=|origyear=|oclc=|doi=|bibcode=|id=|trans-chapter=|chapterurl=|quote=|laysummary=|laydate=}}
* {{cite web|last= Ronsin|first=Francis|url=http://www.iisg.nl/womhist/manfreuk.pdf |title=E. Armand and &quot;la camaraderie amoureuse&quot; – Revolutionary sexualism and the struggle against jealousy |year=2000|access-date=20 September 2010 |deadurl=no |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20110514110104/http://www.iisg.nl/womhist/manfreuk.pdf |archive-date=14 May 2011 |df= |ref=harv}}
* {{cite book |last = Rupert | first = Mark | title = Globalization and International Political Economy | publisher = Rowman &amp; Littlefield Publishers | location = Lanham | year = 2006 | isbn = 978-0-7425-2943-4|ref=harv }}
* {{cite book|last1= Ryley|first1= Peter|chapter=Individualism|editor1-last=Levy|editor1-first=Carl |editor1-link=Carl Levy (political scientist)|editor2-last=Adams|editor2-first=Matthew S. |title=The Palgrave Handbook of Anarchism|year=2019|publisher=[[Springer Publishing]]|isbn=978-3-319-75620-2|ref=harv}}
* {{cite web |last=Ryner |first=Han |title=Mini-Manual of Individualism |year=2007 |orig-year=1905 |publisher=Han Ryner Archive |url=https://www.marxists.org/archive/ryner/1905/mini-manual.htm |ref=harv}}
* {{cite book |last=Sheehan |date=2003 |first=Sean |title=Anarchism |url={{google books|dYTxAQAAQBAJ|plainurl=yes}} |publisher= Reaktion Books |place=London |publicationdate=1 June 2003 |isbn=978-1-86189-169-3 |ref=harv }}
* {{cite book |last=Skirda |first=Alexandre |title=Facing the enemy: a history of anarchist organization from Proudhon to May 1968 |publisher=A.K. Press |year=2002 |isbn=978-1-902593-19-7 |title-link=Facing the Enemy |ref=harv}}
* {{cite book |last=Sylvan |year = 2007 |first=Richard |section=Anarchism |editor=Robert E. Goodin |editor2=Philip Pettit |editor3=Thomas Pogge |title=A Companion to Contemporary Political Philosophy |edition=2nd |url=http://eltalondeaquiles.pucp.edu.pe/wp-content/uploads/2016/04/Robert-E--Goodin-Philip-Pettit-Thomas-W--Pogge-A-Companion-to-Contemporary-Political-Philosophy-2-Volume-Set-Blackwell-Companions-to-Philosophy-2007.pdf |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20170517032711/http://eltalondeaquiles.pucp.edu.pe/wp-content/uploads/2016/04/Robert-E--Goodin-Philip-Pettit-Thomas-W--Pogge-A-Companion-to-Contemporary-Political-Philosophy-2-Volume-Set-Blackwell-Companions-to-Philosophy-2007.pdf |archivedate=17 May 2017 |series=Blackwell Companions to Philosophy |volume=5 |publisher=Blackwell Publishing |isbn= 978-1-4051-3653-2 |authorlink=Richard Sylvan |editorlink=Robert E. Goodin |editorlink2=Philip Pettit |editorlink3=Thomas Pogge|ref=harv }}
* {{cite web|last=Stringham|first=Edward P. |authorlink=Edward Stringham|title=Anarchy, State, and Public Choice|url=http://www.independent.org/publications/tir/article.asp?issueID=53&amp;articleID=686|year =2005|location = Cheltenham, UK| publisher = Edward Elgar|ref=harv}}
* {{cite book|last=Stringham|first=Edward P. |authorlink=Edward Stringham|title=Anarchy and the Law: The Political Economy of Choice|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=yzgrDwAAQBAJ|date=5 July 2017|publisher=Taylor &amp; Francis|isbn=978-1-351-53182-5|ref=harv}}
* {{cite journal |last=Suissa|first=Judith  |url=http://newhumanist.org.uk/1288/anarchy-in-the-classroom|title= Anarchy in the classroom |journal=[[New Humanist]] |volume=120 |issue=5 |year=2007 |orig-year= 2005|ref=harv|access-date=21 January 2010 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20100817005249/http://newhumanist.org.uk/1288/anarchy-in-the-classroom |archive-date=17 August 2010 }}
* {{cite book |last=Suissa  |first=Judith |date=2006|title=Anarchism and Education: A philosophical perspective |url=http://rebels-library.org/files/anarchismandeducation.pdf |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20150402095224/http://rebels-library.org/files/anarchismandeducation.pdf |archivedate=2 April 2015 |publisher=Routledge |place=New York |publicationdate=2006-02-02 |isbn=978-0-415-37194-0 |ref=harv}}
* {{cite book|last=Suissa  |first=Judith |chapter=Anarchist Education|editor1-last=Levy|editor1-first=Carl |editor1-link=Carl Levy (political scientist)|editor2-last=Adams|editor2-first=Matthew S. |title=The Palgrave Handbook of Anarchism|year=2019|chapter-url=https://books.google.com.cy/books/about/The_Palgrave_Handbook_of_Anarchism.html?id=SRyQswEACAAJ&amp;source=kp_book_description&amp;redir_esc=y|publisher=[[Springer Publishing]]|isbn=978-3-319-75620-2|ref=harv}}
* {{cite book|last=Supek|first=Rudi |authorlink=Rudi Supek|title=Self-governing Socialism: Sociology and politics. Economics|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=REg0xPL_NeQC&amp;pg=PA84|year=1975|publisher=M.E. Sharpe|isbn=978-0-87332-050-4|ref=harv}}
* {{cite book |last=Thomas |first=Paul |title=Karl Marx and the Anarchists |publisher=Routledge &amp; Kegan Paul |location=London |year=1985 |isbn=978-0-7102-0685-5 |ref=harv}}
* {{cite book|last1= Turcato|first1= Davide|chapter=Anarchist Communism|editor1-last=Levy|editor1-first=Carl |editor1-link=Carl Levy (political scientist)|editor2-last=Adams|editor2-first=Matthew S. |title=The Palgrave Handbook of Anarchism|year=2019|publisher=[[Springer Publishing]]|isbn=978-3-319-75620-2|ref=harv}}
* {{cite book|last=Vincent|first=Andrew |title=Modern Political Ideologies|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=igrwb3rsOOUC&amp;pg=PR4|year=2010|publisher=John Wiley &amp; Sons|isbn=978-1-4443-1105-1|ref=harv}}
* {{cite book|last=Ward|first=Colin |authorlink=Colin Ward|title=Anarchism: A Very Short Introduction|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=nkgSDAAAQBAJ|date=21 October 2004|publisher=OUP Oxford|isbn=978-0-19-280477-8|ref=harv}}
* {{cite book |last=Wilburn |first=Shawn |chapter=Mutualism|editor1-last=Levy|editor1-first=Carl |editor1-link=Carl Levy (political scientist)|editor2-last=Adams|editor2-first=Matthew S. |title=The Palgrave Handbook of Anarchism|year=2019|publisher=[[Springer Publishing]]|isbn=978-3-319-75620-2|ref=harv}}
* {{cite article|last= Williams|first= Dana M.|title=Contemporary anarchist and anarchistic movements | journal=Sociology Compass | publisher=Wiley | volume=12 | issue=6 | year = 2017 | issn=1751-9020 | doi=10.1111/soc4.12582 | ref=harv}}
* {{cite book|last= Williams|first= Dana M.|chapter=Tactics: Conceptions of Social Change, Revolution, and Anarchist Organisation|editor1-last=Levy|editor1-first=Carl |editor1-link=Carl Levy (political scientist)|editor2-last=Adams|editor2-first=Matthew S. |title=The Palgrave Handbook of Anarchism|year=2019|publisher=[[Springer Publishing]]|isbn=978-3-319-75620-2|ref=harv}}
* {{cite book |last = Wilson | first = A.N. | title = Tolstoy | publisher = W.W. Norton | year = 2001 | url = https://books.google.com/books?id=imYmH8myBUsC&amp;pg=PR19 |  isbn = 978-0-393-32122-7 | ref=harv}}
* {{cite book |last=Woodcock |first=George |title=Anarchism: A History of Libertarian Ideas and Movements |year=1962 |publisher=World Pub. Co. |location=New York |series=Meridian Books |oclc=318155442 |ref=harv}}
* {{cite web |last=Ytak |first=Cathy |date=2000 |title=Anarchisme et naturisme, aujourd'hui |url=http://ytak.club.fr/natytak.html |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20070609184510/http://ytak.club.fr/natytak.html |archive-date=9 June 2007 |ref=harv}}
* {{cite book |last=Zibechi|first=Raul|title=Territories in Resistance: A Cartography of Latin American Social Movements|publisher=AK Press|year=2012|isbn=|location=Oakland|ref=harv}}
* {{cite book |last=Zerzan |first=John |authorlink=John Zerzan |title=Running On Emptiness |year=2002| publisher=Feral House |ref=harv}}
{{refend}}

=== Tertiary ===
{{refbegin|30em|indent=yes}}
* {{cite web|last=Coutinho |first=Steve |title=Zhuangzi – Internet Encyclopedia of Philosophy |date=3 March 2016 |website=iep.utm.edu  |url=http://www.iep.utm.edu/zhuangzi/ |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20160303175106/http://www.iep.utm.edu/zhuangzi/ |archive-date=3 March 2016 |dead-url=no |access-date=5 March 2019 |ref=harv}}
* {{cite book|editor-last=Craig |date=2005 |editor-first=Edward |section=Anarchism |title=The Shorter Routledge Encyclopedia of Philosophy |publicationdate=2005-03-31 |isbn=978-0-415-32495-3 |editorlink=Edward Craig (philosopher) |ref=harv|title-link=Routledge Encyclopedia of Philosophy }}
* {{cite encyclopedia |last= Fiala|first= Andrew|author-link= | title= Anarchism| encyclopedia= [[Stanford Encyclopedia of Philosophy]]|year=2017|url= https://plato.stanford.edu/entries/anarchism/|ref= harv|publisher= Metaphysics Research Lab, Stanford University}}
* {{cite book|last=Hamowy|first=Ronald |title=The Encyclopedia of Libertarianism|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=yxNgXs3TkJYC&amp;pg=PT50|date=15 August 2008|publisher=SAGE|isbn=978-1-4129-6580-4|ref=harv}}
* {{cite SEP|last=Leopold|first=David|url-id=max-stirner|title=Max Stirner|date=4 August 2006 |ref=harv}}
* {{cite book|last1 = McLean|first1 = Iain| first2 = Alistair | last2 = McMillan|title=The Concise Oxford Dictionary of Politics |url= https://books.google.com/books?id=rNJjQgAACAAJ|year=2003|publisher=Oxford University Press|isbn=978-0-19-280276-7| ref = harv}}
* {{cite book|last=Miller|first=David |title=The Blackwell Encyclopaedia of Political Thought|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=NIZfQTd3nSMC|date=26 August 1991|publisher=Wiley|isbn=978-0-631-17944-3|ref=harv}}
* {{cite book|first = Geoffrey| last = Ostergaard|year =2003| authorlink= Geoffrey Ostergaard| title = The Blackwell Dictionary of Modern Social Thought| publisher =Blackwell Publishing|ref = harv}}
* {{cite book|last=Outhwaite|first=William|title=The Blackwell Dictionary of Modern Social Thought|chapter-url=https://books.google.com/books?id=JJmdpqJwkwwC&amp;pg=PA14|date= 2008|publisher=John Wiley &amp; Sons|isbn=978-0-470-99901-1|page=14|chapter=Anarcho-Syndicalism|ref = harv}}
* {{cite web| title=Definition of ANARCHISM | website=Merriam-Webster | year=2019 | url=https://www.merriam-webster.com/dictionary/anarchism |ref={{sfnref | Definition of Anarchism by Merriam-Webster |2019}}| access-date=2019-02-28}}
* {{cite SEP|last=Philp|first=Mark|url-id=godwin|title=William Godwin|date=20 May 2006 |ref=harv}}
* {{cite book|last=Trevijano|first=Carmen García|editor=Ted Honderich|title=Enciclopedia Oxford de filosofía|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=s9iwZGv44psC&amp;pg=PA402|year=2001|publisher=Tecnos|isbn=978-84-309-3699-1|ref=harv}}{{refend}}

== Further reading ==
* {{cite book|last=Barclay|first=Harold B. |authorlink=Harold Barclay|title=People Without Government: An Anthropology of Anarchy|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=MrFHQgAACAAJ|year=1990|publisher=Kahn &amp; Averill|isbn=978-0-939306-09-1}}
* {{cite book|last=Harper|first=Clifford |authorlink=Clifford Harper|title=Anarchy: A Graphic Guide|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=W63aAAAAMAAJ|year=1987|publisher=Camden Press|isbn=978-0-948491-22-1}}
* {{cite book|last =Le Guin|first =Ursula K.|authorlink=Ursula K. Le Guin|title=The Dispossessed|date=2009|publisher=HarperCollins|title-link =The Dispossessed}} An utopian science fiction novel
* {{cite book|last=Kinna|first=Ruth |title=Anarchism: A Beginners Guide|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=LLLaAAAAMAAJ|year=2005|publisher=Oneworld|isbn=978-1-85168-370-3}}
* {{cite book|last=Sartwell|first= Crispin|author-link=Crispin Sartwell|title=Against the state: an introduction to anarchist political theory|publisher=SUNY Press|year=2008|isbn=978-0-7914-7447-1|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=bk-aaMVGKO0C}}
* [[James C. Scott|Scott, James C.]], (2012) ''[[Two Cheers for Anarchism: Six Easy Pieces on Autonomy, Dignity, and Meaningful Work and Play]]'', Princeton, NJ: Princeton University Press {{ISBN|978-0-691-15529-6}}.
* {{cite book|last= Wolff|first=Robert Paul|authorlink=Robert Paul Wolff|title=In Defense of Anarchism|year=1998|publisher=University of California Press|isbn=978-0-520-21573-3|title-link=In Defense of Anarchism}}

== External links ==
{{Sister project links|voy=no|n=no|v=no|b=Subject:Anarchism|s=Portal:Anarchism|d=Q6199|c=Category:Anarchism}}
* [http://dwardmac.pitzer.edu/ Anarchy Archives]. [[Anarchy Archives]] is an online research center on the history and theory of anarchism
&lt;!-- Attention! The external link portion of this article regularly grows far beyond manageable size. PLEASE only list an outside link if it applies to anarchism in general, is somewhat noteworthy, and has consensus on the talkpage. Links to sites which cover anarchist submovements will be routinely moved to subarticles to keep this article free of clutter. --&gt;
{{prone to spam|date=November 2014}}
{{Z148}}&lt;!-- {{no more links}}. Please be cautious adding more external links. Wikipedia is not a collection of links and should not be used for advertising. Excessive or inappropriate links will be removed. See [[Wikipedia:External links]] and [[Wikipedia:Spam]] for details. If there are already suitable links, propose additions or replacements on the article's talk page, or submit your link to the relevant category at DMOZ (dmoz.org) — now curlie.org — and link there using {{curlie}}. --&gt;

{{Anarchism}}
{{Anarchies}}
{{Philosophy topics}}
{{Political culture}}
{{Political ideologies}}
{{Social and political philosophy}}
{{Aspects of capitalism}}
{{Good article}}
{{Authority control}}
[[Category:Anarchism| ]]
[[Category:Anti-capitalism]]
[[Category:Anti-fascism]]
[[Category:Far-left politics]]
[[Category:Libertarian socialism]]
[[Category:Political culture]]
[[Category:Political ideologies]]
[[Category:Social theories]]</text>
      <sha1>jhdi5dbheuxjjjs9wtm1jzwy108rrod</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>AfghanistanHistory</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>13</id>
    <redirect title="History of Afghanistan" />
    <revision>
      <id>783865149</id>
      <parentid>74466652</parentid>
      <timestamp>2017-06-05T04:18:18Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Tom.Reding</username>
        <id>9784415</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>+{{Redirect category shell}} using [[Project:AWB|AWB]]</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">#REDIRECT [[History of Afghanistan]]

{{Redirect category shell|1=
{{R from CamelCase}}
}}</text>
      <sha1>iv7s0lr40b17x33tfb0caa2g5bplgrk</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>AfghanistanGeography</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>14</id>
    <redirect title="Geography of Afghanistan" />
    <revision>
      <id>783865160</id>
      <parentid>407008307</parentid>
      <timestamp>2017-06-05T04:18:23Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Tom.Reding</username>
        <id>9784415</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>+{{Redirect category shell}} using [[Project:AWB|AWB]]</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">#REDIRECT [[Geography of Afghanistan]]

{{Redirect category shell|1=
{{R from CamelCase}}
}}</text>
      <sha1>39r4w8qg62iexlyskf0ga3tblagtl8x</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>AfghanistanPeople</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>15</id>
    <redirect title="Demographics of Afghanistan" />
    <revision>
      <id>783865293</id>
      <parentid>616420354</parentid>
      <timestamp>2017-06-05T04:19:42Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Tom.Reding</username>
        <id>9784415</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>+{{Redirect category shell}} using [[Project:AWB|AWB]]</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">#REDIRECT [[Demographics of Afghanistan]]

{{Redirect category shell|1=
{{R from CamelCase}}
}}</text>
      <sha1>fncm9bh9l25bmvyzq21zopijbuqq3nd</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>AfghanistanCommunications</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>18</id>
    <redirect title="Communications in Afghanistan" />
    <revision>
      <id>783865299</id>
      <parentid>74466499</parentid>
      <timestamp>2017-06-05T04:19:45Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Tom.Reding</username>
        <id>9784415</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>+{{Redirect category shell}} using [[Project:AWB|AWB]]</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">#REDIRECT [[Communications in Afghanistan]]

{{Redirect category shell|1=
{{R from CamelCase}}
}}</text>
      <sha1>q8gdi8070w6yitd4hqev68pn5niog3x</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>AfghanistanTransportations</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>19</id>
    <redirect title="Transport in Afghanistan" />
    <revision>
      <id>783821589</id>
      <parentid>409266982</parentid>
      <timestamp>2017-06-04T21:42:11Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Tom.Reding</username>
        <id>9784415</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>+{{R category shell}} using [[Project:AWB|AWB]]</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">#REDIRECT [[Transport in Afghanistan]]

{{Redirect category shell|1=
 {{R from CamelCase}}
{{R unprintworthy}}
}}</text>
      <sha1>miah0hk4ws6ctake8y0nezxq30vn61p</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>AfghanistanMilitary</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>20</id>
    <redirect title="Afghan Armed Forces" />
    <revision>
      <id>783821738</id>
      <parentid>558328133</parentid>
      <timestamp>2017-06-04T21:43:11Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Tom.Reding</username>
        <id>9784415</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>+{{R category shell}} using [[Project:AWB|AWB]]</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">#REDIRECT [[Afghan Armed Forces]]

{{Redirect category shell|1=
 {{R from CamelCase}}
}}</text>
      <sha1>j013t2shx5j3p2gq4cjzap2fjykxklg</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>AfghanistanTransnationalIssues</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>21</id>
    <redirect title="Foreign relations of Afghanistan" />
    <revision>
      <id>783821743</id>
      <parentid>46448859</parentid>
      <timestamp>2017-06-04T21:43:14Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Tom.Reding</username>
        <id>9784415</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>+{{R category shell}} using [[Project:AWB|AWB]]</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">#REDIRECT [[Foreign relations of Afghanistan]]

{{Redirect category shell|1=
 {{R from CamelCase}}
}}</text>
      <sha1>80xx3tzgvcdioufir5addc3wn177se3</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>AssistiveTechnology</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>23</id>
    <redirect title="Assistive technology" />
    <revision>
      <id>783865310</id>
      <parentid>74466798</parentid>
      <timestamp>2017-06-05T04:19:50Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Tom.Reding</username>
        <id>9784415</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>+{{Redirect category shell}} using [[Project:AWB|AWB]]</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">#REDIRECT [[Assistive_technology]]

{{Redirect category shell|1=
{{R from CamelCase}}
}}
</text>
      <sha1>f0x0fdqkexsha1xdm4wiuw302xhw2yc</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>